[Music]
Hello, good evening, good day,
everybody, and welcome to the
geopolitics episode of the Ask Abhijit
Show. I hope you are all doing
fantastic. Let us see who all is there
on the live chat. Let me greet some of
you
before we begin with the questions. So,
what who do we have? We have Vamshi
Reddy from Twitter or X really now from
Riva Madhya Pradesh.
IPK 1S Namaskaram Chitan Aradhya RJ Are
you seeing Ashtavakra? Shub Dipawali,
happy Dipawali, happy Diwali, Diwali,
Shub Diwali to everybody, all of you,
and your families and your loved ones.
Uh we have beneath, we have Vladimir
Putin Jai Shri Ramji wise idiot, boxer
Apurva Anupama.
Good evening. Sa Shiva Sai Sharan Chitan
Aradhya Animesh Namaste Shamit Bringi
Shamit Bringi Dev. Hello and happy
Diwali. Animals from laugh from animals
for laugh from Mumbai. Avinash beneath
Bonjour. Geopolitical way here from
Indore. Good evening, sir. Sharan Shivam
Shukla Tanmay Deshpande Really now Mr.
Jam Hare Krishna.
Apurva once again Jay Desai Tathagat
Karan Daksh Jai Shri Ram Ram Ram Komal
Hello Anando MS Shivam Shukla R PPL from
Washington. Well, good to have you. Good
morning. Chintan Hello Rahul G from
Kolhapur. Good to have you, sir. Thank
you. Dev is here Jai Jagannath from
Odisha.
Sharan from Bangalore Kiran Kiran Jha
Ram Ram Anirudh
Parakala Anirudh Parakala
uh
Anahita Good evening, happy Diwali.
Uh Ananta Subramaniam Prachit Agarwal
Radhe Game Changer
Rishi Moria Arjun Priyanshi Sood Hello
Om
Uh Venkat Murli K
uh Boxer is here from Pune. RJ gives a
lot of hearts with lot of hearts back to
you. Rishikesh Dash Dasgupta Hello
Pratar Dana Namaste Dur Durdarshan
Nice. Uh Lucky Plays Hello Channel PSJH
Hi Some next space Ashtavakra once again
Bruce Wayne Shub Choti Diwali. Yes, same
user.
Um
Manisha Kardoso Namaste One of two Happy
Diwali RJ Lots of hearts
Uh Credit Ends
is here.
Um
Mary Cain Happy Diwali. Thank you so
much, ma'am. I hope Well, happy Diwali
to you as well. Thank you.
Uh Como estas says Akash Patel. Well,
all good. Thank you. Jenil Event
Countdown Injured Soccer Player
Jasdeep Saran is here from Chicago.
Jayant Madika Maddika Jayant Maddika
Hello.
Vamshi once again Ayush Dipali Deepika
Abhishek Shrivastav Vinay Rai Saurabh
Shukla Kiran Jha Okay, let me stop
greeting you all otherwise I can do that
all day. Let's get going with some
questions. What questions do we have?
Dev is a new member. Thank you so much,
Dev. Good to have you. I really
appreciate your support. Thank you very
much.
Okay, this drummer 1989 says is Trump
really administering
or is he just there to increase his net
worth through cryptocurrency?
I'm sure he is administering and doing
his job as the president of the US, but
he is also seems to be
kind of double tasking, multitasking.
So, he has first of all, made sure that
he is not directly in charge of his
business empire. He has created entities
and handed over the control on paper
legally, officially
to various family members, his sons, and
so on.
So, he is not directly
uh you know, administering his business
empire and controlling the business
empire.
Uh but you will see that wherever he
goes, where he for for example, he
recently a few months ago went to Oman
or the Middle East, and there was a lot
of business feeling as well that
happened as part of his visit, maybe on
the sidelines, but still it was it was
there.
And
the government of which country was it?
Oman was it? Qatar? One of these
countries that gave him a gigantic uh
uh 747 jet, I think it was. Yeah, Boeing
747 or something like that, something
similar, very large jet. That's clearly
a kickback or a bribe. I mean,
definitely a bribe or inducement of some
kind, but well, he takes it. So, that's
his style.
But he certainly is
doing his job as the president of the
United States. No question about that.
He is doing what is required of him,
and his objective is to be the biggest,
baddest, greatest ever president of the
US, at least this side of Abraham
Lincoln, if not all of all time. That's
his great ambition.
And he is he Well, he he wants to
end as many wars as possible. That's one
uh achievement that that's one set of
achievements he wants to have. So, maybe
he's asked various uh
various nations to start wars so that he
can end them, perhaps. Maybe the
Pakistanis are doing that. Maybe
maybe that's why they they they have
been provoking Afghanistan. Maybe
they'll provoke us as well. Let's see.
So, that's what he is doing.
Uh Shamit Bringi Bringi Dev says,
"Will India-China relations become more
positive over the next 10 years, given
that President Trump has slapped both
nations with high trade tariffs?"
It is certainly possible
that
for the short to medium term,
India-China relations will get better
better to some extent.
I am very doubtful that the core issues
will get will be resolved. The core
issue in the two in the relationship
between the two nations is the
undemarcated India-Tibet border.
So, I don't expect that to be resolved.
The Chinese don't want to resolve that.
I'll be very surprised and very
pleasantly surprised if that happens,
but I think it's unlikely
hm for that that that will happen.
Beyond that, I believe that there will
be various
you know, means of cooperation
or or at least working together and
setting aside the core issue temporarily
for a while, for maybe 5-10 years,
perhaps, maximum 20 years. So, all I
expect that the relationship will become
more positive.
Um
as long as Trump is around and as long
as this current approach of the
uh United States continues or maybe gets
worse.
So, Trump is just the current
manifestation of the United States and
its new approach towards the world.
And uh see, Trump is going to be around
for another 3 and 1/2 or so years, and
that's this is the second term. So,
clearly if if everything goes as per
the way things are, uh they should, then
there will be a new president
uh by 2020 whatever it is. What What
what 2028?
Yeah, 20 2029, I suppose, 2029.
And then if things change, then
India-China relationship may once again
diverge or whatever. So, it all depends
on the attitude of the US. When you have
a very powerful external enemy that is
targeting both of you, it kind of makes
sense to at least for some time set
aside the bigger differences and try and
cooperate in in various other ways.
Bhaskar Khatwal says, "Many other
characters in world history like a
certain sergeant major in the
magnificent Shri Nehru." I'm not sure,
sir. Today we discuss geopolitics, sir.
Let's discuss geopolitics. Okay, I
cannot mix and match every time. When I
do history sessions, people ask me
geopolitics questions. When I'm doing
geopolitics, people ask me history
questions. I would say that
Look,
Sergeant Major Gandhi and Shri Nehru,
are there other other figures like that?
There are other figures like that, I
would imagine. You know, people who have
uh
played certain roles. But let's discuss
geopolitics today.
Bhaskar says, "Alignment with Gandhar
today is good." Well, now geopolitics
question from Bhaskar G once again.
Okay,
"Alignment with Gandhar today is good
because it furthers our interest.
But why do some say that Bharat has
civilizational connect with Afghanistan?
What kind in spite of what happened at
Hindu Kush range and other stuff the
past 1,000 years?"
See, the reason people say that we have
a civilizational connect with with
Gandhar with Afghanistan is because
historically Gandhar was part of our
civilizational territory. It was part of
Bharatvarsha. It was part of Jambudweep.
Um and Gandhar has been integrated and
and part of our civilization since at
least the Mahabharat times, as we know
very well, right? Uh
The mother of the Kauravas, who's known
as Gandhari, she was from Gandhar. She
was you could say an Afghan. From
today's perspective, she was Afghan. So
was her brother, Shakuni.
Pretty evil guy, wasn't he? Pretty
Machiavellian guy. Not Not Chanakyan
guy, but Machiavellian guy.
And we have historical records that do
indicate that Gandhara was even part of
our civilization about 1,500 or so years
ago.
Uh you have Xuanzang coming in from
China and the moment he sets foot in
Gandhara, he says, "Thank God, I'm
finally in India after all these years
of of trudging across the mountain
ranges and deserts and and barely
surviving, I'm finally in in in India."
The moment he reaches what is now
Afghanistan, he says he writes that,
right?
So, it was part of our civilization
civilization until about 1,000 AD.
And the people are connected to us
are related to us, not just culturally,
but also genetically. The Pashtuns are
an extension of the of the larger
northern Indian population.
Right? So, that's why we do have this
connection, but today culturally,
civilizationally, there's nothing in
common between us and them. Yeah, if you
see the body language of Pashtuns and
Afghans, it's more more Indian than
Iranian, clearly, or more Indian than
Central Asian. They all speak some kind
of Hindi, which they call it Urdu or
whatever, right?
So, it is clearly there.
They We understand each other very well
because we are essentially the same
people even if if it's been 1,000 years
of the since they've been converted.
Uh
and uh
So, because of all these reasons,
it is clear that we have or we had a
civilizational connect with Afghanistan.
Uh and if you see so So, that's that's
in the past, but today we still have
those connections. We still understand
each other very well. We still If you if
you have a Look,
if you have an Afghan person walking
around in India, people won't even look
twice at the at the person, right? They
look like us. They behave like us. They
they They We understand each other very
well and so on. So, there is a
civilizational connect because of this.
What happened in the Hindu Kush range
and and so on, that was Turkic.
The Turks
from Central Asia were They had
conquered various parts of India
and they carried away maybe several
million Indian women and children mostly
as slaves to the slave markets of
Bukhara and
Samarkand, yes? And that obviously had
to be done through the Khyber Pass and
the Upari Siyena Mountains, which are
now called the Hindu Kush Mountains.
Upari Siyena means
uh
those mountains where even eagles can't
fly higher.
Upari Siyena. The The The Urdu word or
Persian word Shaheen comes from the
Sanskrit word Siyena,
which means eagle.
So, Upari Siyena means uh
mountains that are higher than where
eagles fly.
That's how tall these mountains were and
and are, I suppose. So, that was the
original
word or term
or name for this mountain range, but
because so many Hindus died there while
crossing those mountains, while being
carried across those mountains as
slaves, that's why they are now called
the Hindu Kush Mountains, the killer of
the Hindus. I suppose if you dig in the
snows there, you will find frozen bodies
from that time, 1,000 years ago, in the
past 1,000 years.
Okay, Bhaskar once again says, "What is
the significance of Mr. Henry Kissinger?
Why is he an important figure in
history, geopolitics, and diplomacy?
What was he instrumental in?" You see
this book here, this big fat white book
here?
That is
Diplomacy
by Henry Kissinger.
Um he was a global statesman. See,
what's his story in brief? He was
Jewish. Um he was born in Germany
and
um he migrated to the United States
and he went on to become the Secretary
of State of the United States, which is
the same position as our foreign
minister, Minister of External Affairs.
So, in the US, it's called the Secretary
of State. You know, the head of the
State Department, which is the Ministry
of External Affairs, so to say.
And he
held this position during the
presidency of Shri Nixon,
right?
The Nixon-Kissinger era.
Um
and Kissinger was was was a very
effective uh Secretary of State, a very
Machiavellian person, no question about
that.
Um He had a pretty, you could say, nasty
approach towards India. He is the person
who kind of engineered the US uh China
detente.
Right? The US-China rapprochement.
Kissinger and Nixon go to Beijing and
they meet with Mao and Zhou Enlai and so
on, and that brings about this thaw
between the two nations. So, Kissinger
was instrumental in so much of what
happened in the 20th century and a lot
of the
major changes that happened and even
after Nixon was impeached and
uh who was it? Carter comes to power, I
suppose. Carter Carter was brought in.
Even after that, Kissinger kind of
remained
continued to play the role of an elder
statesman who understood the world very,
very well.
And you know, his advice was always
sought, maybe behind closed doors or
whatever, that sort of thing.
And yeah, so and and he was kind of a
scholar. He wrote a lot of books. He
wrote a book about China. He wrote a
book about
leadership. He wrote a book about
diplomacy. He's got He's got lot of
writings, very interesting writings,
okay? Very, very well-written books. You
can learn a lot from those things and so
on. So, and and he knew essentially
every world leader that uh existed or
that lived uh during that period in
time. And he only tragically passed away
a I don't know, a year or so ago. Yeah,
so
Yeah, so that's why he was a central
figure
in the geopolitics of his times and
geopolitics eventually becomes history.
So, that's the deal.
Okay, Bhaskar once again. Bhaskar has a
lot of questions. Well, let us take the
questions. Why is Fergana Valley The
Fergana Valley region in Central Asia
considered to be a breeding ground
ground for terrorism? What does Russia
do to make sure Gehra Rajya or the deep
state does not grow snakes in Russia's
backyard for mischievous purposes?
Okay, we're going to go and check out
the Fergana Valley. Give me a second
while I while I pull up the map.
We must pull up the map and we shall
look at the Fergana Valley. What is this
place?
Fergana Valley. One second, one second,
one second. Where's the map? All right,
here we go. Here we go. Let's put that
on the screen.
Uzbekistan we are talking about.
Uzbekistan.
Here we are. So, we go to Central Asia
and we go north of India and west of
India
and we have this country called
Uzbekistan.
Now, if you go to Uzbekistan, uh you
have all these nations cities and so on
called
Yeah.
So, where is Andijan? Let's zoom in a
little bit more.
Andijan Andijan Andijan is here,
Fergana.
So, there is this town called Fergana
and there is this uh other town called
Andijan. Andijan is famous for two
things. First of all, it was the
birthplace of Zahir-ud-din, also known
as Babur,
the first king of the Mughal Empire of
the Mughal Kingdom.
So, he was born here in Andijan. If you
go to the satellite image, it makes it
make a little more sense.
Uh so, that's the first thing that
Andijan is famous for, for being the
birthplace of the Mughal King Babur.
And the second thing Andijan is famous
for is the Andijan massacre, which
happened about 20-ish years ago.
And we'll not go into that.
Um so,
this region, Fergana,
well, it's a pretty, you could say, you
know,
um conservative place,
a place you where you have uh
where you have this uh
conservative
Islam Islamic kind of
you know,
a traditional approach to life.
Uh that's that's one thing.
But if you, you know, the thing is that
today
Tajikistan seems to be more of an
epicenter
of terrorism and all kinds of nasty
stuff. I mean, recently you had some
some terrorist attacks in
in Russia,
which emanated essentially out of
Tajikistan, not quite from Fergana. And
Tajikistan is not a Turkic nation. It's
an Indo-Iranian nation, right? It's it's
right next door to India, actually, if
you look.
We Indians don't even realize that. Uh
anyhow, so Fergana is That's the deal
about Fergana. Uh this region is called
the Fergana Valley and
historically, it's been the, you know,
the the
the place where the Mughal Kingdom
originated. And it's it's a pretty
conservative place, kind of, you could
say, similar to Dagestan
or Chechnya, which is like pretty far
away.
Uh
but
I personally don't consider Fergana to
be that much of a breeding ground for
terrorism compared to a
place like Pakistan.
You don't have the situation in Fergana
that you have in Pakistan, where you
have
tremendous amounts of funding which is
poured into terrorism. You have
terrorism, you know, schools, colleges,
universities, IITs, or whatever, you
know, institutes of terrorism. You don't
have all of that in in Fergana. You have
that fundamentalist mindset to some
extent.
Uh
but you don't have the situation that
you have in Pakistan.
Now, coming to the other question. Why
the What does Russia do to make sure the
deep state doesn't grow snakes in
Russia's backyard?
Well, it has The Russians have a pretty
powerful, pretty
pretty competent intelligence agency,
right? Which keeps an eye on what's
happening and it's it's certainly does
coordinate with these countries in in
Central Asia. All the stans, the
Russians have significantly robust
um you know, um
uh cooperation with these nations and
coordination with these nations.
And
wherever you may have, you know, snakes
emerging, Those snakes, their heads are
crushed
quietly.
That's how it is done.
It all happens behind the scenes, cloak
and dagger stuff, where everything goes.
You know?
Okay.
Bhaskar once again says, "What was the
Yalta Conference?
Are we anticipating such an event coming
soon in coming 30-50 years time? Why is
the US government scared of own army's
body bags?" I don't know what that
means, but
the Yalta Conference threw threw up very
images, okay? Let's let's do that. Let's
take a look at that. So, you have the
four great leaders okay, of that time.
Roosevelt, Stalin, and so on, okay?
Yalta Conference.
Okay, let's take some Let's take a look
at some some images.
So, here we have three of the big
biggies. You have Roosevelt, you have
Stalin, you have Churchill.
Very famous images come out of here.
Yalta.
Um
yeah.
So, yeah, it it it threw up these very
interesting, very famous, very iconic
images that came essentially at the end
of
the the Second World War. And so, what
was the Yalta Yalta Conference
essentially? So, it was Look,
by early 1945, it it the writing on the
wall was clear that the Allies were
going to win.
Uh the Axis, which is Hitler and
Mussolini and the Japanese Empire, they
were going to lose. It was very clear.
So, the three nations See, at that time,
France was not quite a
It had been under German occupation. It
had been liberated, but it did not did
not really have a government. Uh Charles
de Gaulle was in exile for most of the
war. He wasn't in the West, in the UK.
So, he wasn't there in the conference.
So, you have the three big guys
who were able to resist the the Germans.
The United States,
the UK,
and Russia.
The UK was never occupied, so it stayed
independent. The US anyway was never
under any danger, and Russia did most of
the fighting, most of the dying, and
most of the winning.
So, these three then come together, and
they kind of
essentially decide what the world order
is going to be like once the war
eventually ends, whenever it does.
So, that was
what essentially the Yalta Conference
was all about. Are we anticipating such
events
in the coming 30 to 50 years time?
Um
you know, that sort of an event happens
only when a war a big war is ending. We
don't want big wars, first of all. Uh
hopefully, there will be no big war, in
which case no such event will happen.
I'm not sure of army body bags and all.
I'm not sure what you're asking there.
So, yeah.
Rithik Powar says, "What are the ways to
weaken the US Empire?"
What are the ways to weaken the US
Empire?
Um I don't think anyone's really in a
position to weaken the US Empire. What
you can do is grow your own strength.
Right? And and resist the bullying and
whatever coercion is attempted.
So, the point is
um
the way to
You you can't really weaken the US
Empire as such, but you can make its
relative strength less strong by
becoming more powerful yourself. That's
what you can do.
And that's what the US wants to prevent.
It wants to prevent nations like China,
Russia, India from becoming more
powerful. And that's all what all the
current action is all about, you know?
Uh economic and diplomatic and other
other action.
Yeah, uh tariffs and sanctions and
semiconductor restrictions and AI and
all that. That's what it's all about.
So, you don't really weaken the US
Empire, you grow your own strength, you
become more powerful, you grow your
economy, you grow your military might,
your naval might. Um
um
you know, ballistic missiles, other
kinds of missiles, technology, AI,
space, all of that.
And that's how you relatively become
less weak compared to the US. That's
what you can do.
Bhaskar Kayatwal says, "Happy Diwali to
you and your family, sir." Thank you
very much. I wish the same to everyone
who's watching and to you as well,
Bhaskar ji.
Um thank you for everything you do.
Thank you. Endless gratitude for
fortunate to learn and raise our
standards. Love you. Thank you so much.
Thank you very much.
Uh looking forward to meet you again in
JD Summit. Okay, we did. And greetings
from Moscow. Oh, yes, you're from
Moscow. Okay, okay, okay, okay. I
remember meeting you. Thank you so much,
sir. I really appreciate that.
And I'll look forward to meeting you
at JD.
Thank you, sir. Thank you.
Bhaskar says, "If civilizations
rise and fall in a cycle, can this rule
not apply to the to America? If they
develop AGI or or if Elon Musk takes
them to Mars for coloniza- for colon-
colonizing,
then that might make the US dominant for
the next 1,000 years."
It's a possibility. Civilizations do
rise and fall in a cycle. That's what
history has taught us.
Every civilization that came eventually
fell.
We are still around,
but we may also fall. Right now, we are
on very shaky ground. We are losing
touch with our civil- civilizational
roots in India.
So, we are the weakest we've ever been
civilizationally right now.
Right?
Right now, we are pretty deracinated.
We are no longer in touch with our
native languages, with our
civilizational language. We no longer
really practice our culture.
We are more and more enamored with
Western ways. We believe most of our
people have this massive inferiority
complex, which is ever increasing, and
they believe the Western ways are the
best, are better.
So, lots of people are abandoning their
culture and civilization. There is this
massive industrial scale uh
you know,
demographic re-engineering that's
happening in front of the government's
eyes, and nothing is being done about
it, you know?
So, we are super weak right now. We may
also fall as a civilization. In 100
years, maybe all Indians will be
practicing a different religion. It's
very possible. Uh so, anyway, coming
back to what you're asking, can this
rule not apply to the US? Of course, it
can apply to the US.
If they develop AGI or Elon Musk takes
them takes them to Mars and for for
starting colonies there,
um that could make the US dominant for
long time. That's entirely possible. But
eventually, see, this applies more
to empires than to civilizations.
Civilizations sometimes take much longer
to rise and fall.
But empires typically, from what I have
seen, they last about 300 250 to 350
years.
You have some exceptions, but generally,
on average on average
the typical empire lasts about, if it's
a good empire, powerful empire, maybe
250 to 350 years.
So, the US was born in what? 1776. It
became an empire, let's say, in the 19th
century.
Uh so, it's been around as an empire for
about 200-250 years, maybe 100 years
more, perhaps. Even with AGI or
whatever, if they do if they get things
right, they may be around for another
200 years.
Even 1,000 years is possible, but
eventually, everything
you know, ends. So, it applies to
everybody, including the US.
Bhaskar has become a new member. Thank
you very much, sir. Thank you very much.
Thank you. Appreciate that
very much.
Really now says, "Sir, Mayne 26/11 ke
bare mein
padha hai aur
kaha ja sakta par ab main a country in
Middle East ke prati indifferent rehne
ke bajaye unke bare mein
bhaybheet aur krodhit mahsus
karne lagi hoon."
Okay.
Uh so, what the lady is saying is that
um
I've read about the 26/11 and what
happened there,
and it is becoming more clear, according
to her, that um
that the truth hasn't really come out in
the public domain.
And she is really uh
um
concerned and angry with the certain
country in the Middle East.
Increasingly so.
Well, yeah. It's it's possible that, you
know, Look, even when it comes to 9/11,
uh if you watch what Tucker Tucker
Carlson is putting out on YouTube these
days, he's claiming that there's been a
massive cover-up. And the truth has
never been put out in front of the
people of the United States.
When it comes to 1963, the assassination
of John F. Kennedy, once again, that's a
massive cover-up.
So, it's entirely possible that maybe
there could be some kind of cover-up in
26/11,
and maybe some countries may be involved
to larger or lesser extent than what we
have imagined, whichever they are. It's
possible. It's possible.
And uh
yeah, so maybe new facts will eventually
someday come to light.
It's possible. Okay.
Okay, Dibyayan says, "The major
religions in sub-Saharan Africa today is
Christianity and Islam. Were they
brought there by invaders and wiped out
the indigenous religions?" Look, today
we're going to discuss geopolitics, but
to answer your question in brief,
they were of course brought in there by
invaders and colonizers
and occupiers and barbarians, genocidal
barbarians. And these
outsiders did wipe out the indigenous
religions.
Right? By imposing their religions, they
can control the people more. They can
control the society
in a in a better way, in a in a stronger
way, by which and by doing that, they
can extract more resources.
Right? So, that's the overall objective.
So, yes, indeed, that's the case. That
has been the case.
Dibyayan says, "Can the US put all its
debt in crypto and then devalue it?" I
think that seems to be the plan right
now. That's what the Russians are
saying, and that does seem to be pretty
likely
plan of the US to, you know,
put all their debt into crypto, then
devalue the crypto, and
the debt evaporates.
They certainly can do it. I think that's
that seems to be the
um
the direction in which things are going.
Makes sense to do that.
Varun Bajaj says, you say that the US
You say the US would war
if key nations, China, Russia, India
drop the USD.
Sovereignty, legal \ moral
justification
contradicts US champion in independence.
There's no legal moral justification for
this.
You don't need legal moral justification
to remain number one.
I am number one. I'm the most powerful
nation.
And I'm the most powerful because so and
so conditions have been created by me.
If somebody wants to undo those
conditions, I don't care whether there
are no legal justifications or moral
just moral justifications.
I am the strongest and that's the only
justification I need to do what what is
required.
Why do I conquer? Because I can.
I don't need a legal or moral
justification.
Please understand the world doesn't
operate on the basis of law
or legality or morality.
I think that's something I've been
drilling harping on about since the year
2001.
Since 2001 I've been saying this
that there is no morality in in
geopolitics. Laws don't matter. Laws are
made for the weak.
Laws are made by the strong and applied
to the imposed on the weak.
The strong nations don't follow any
laws.
There is no morality in geopolitics.
That's what Vishnu Gupta Chanakya taught
you all, but you people don't listen.
If the US champions human rights and
democracy, does it really
walk the talk?
Don't they support dictatorships?
Don't they support Pakistani the
Pakistani military?
Does the Pakistani military respect
human rights, democracy?
It's a terrorist regime. The US supports
that. The US funded and financed
Pakistani terrorism for decades against
us.
You see any
US champion independence
morality, legality, human rights,
democracy there?
Come on.
Come on. Please. Let's let's grow up a
little bit. Please all of all of us.
Rohit Suneja says, which country
actually has the best education system?
This has nothing to do with geopolitics,
sir. I'm not sure who who does. I think
when it comes to science and technology,
the West, the US may still be the best.
Tanmay says, no kings protest democracy
or deep state ploy.
It's just to keep up the semblance of
democracy and, you know, freedom of
expression in the US.
Uh the Democrats most likely are behind
this or maybe their allied
uh
people. But, yeah, there's no deep state
ploy in that. I assure you of that.
Game Changer says, does the brain work
in a deterministic way? Please tell.
What does this have to do with
geopolitics?
We don't know how the brain works. We
don't know. That's a big mystery, okay?
Anantha Subramanian says, how to make
India a superpower like America?
Number two, how to make India industrial
power? Three, what can we learn from
geopolitics that we can apply from life
in life? First num
Number one, let us forget the word the
term superpower. Let us delete the term
superpower from our vocabulary. That
will be better for Indians. Right now we
are we are a third world country and
we're talking about superpower. You want
to be superpower, you want to be
vishwaguru. We should delete those terms
from our vocabulary.
Let us be a decently competent power
first.
We have so many issues and we want to be
superpower.
Because we believe that words make us a
superpower, right? We are a nation of
slogans, not action.
So, forget about the superpower
Forget about it. You can't fly when you
don't even know how to run.
Okay? So, forget that. How to make India
an industrial power? By building up
industries, by making by bring build by
bringing merit into India.
By ending the god damned reservations,
by cleaning up the education system.
Right?
By ensuring that the best talent doesn't
want to leave India the moment they get
a chance.
That's how you make India an industrial
power. By cutting all the red tape, by
making it easier to do business, far
easier to do business in India. By
ending the god damned corruption.
These are the things we can do to make
India an industrial power.
Until we
Unless we do these things, we will
we are destined to remain mediocre.
Okay?
Uh what can we learn from geopolitics
that we can apply in life? Everything in
geopolitics can be applied in life.
Everything.
Right?
Everything
Look, like I said just a while ago.
Laws and rules are made by the powerful.
They apply to the weak.
And the powerful people don't really
play by the rules and laws they've made.
That applies in real life, too.
And
there are so many elements in geo of
geopolitics. Like, for example, you work
Nations work together and become
friends, so to say, or allies when their
interests align or converge. And they
are destined to be adversaries if their
interests diverge. These are This
applies in real life, also.
And diplomacy, all these things are also
apply equally in real life. You just
need to understand the parallels. Right?
So, everything in geopolitics does apply
to real life. Please understand that.
You need to understand how to
transpose
it from geo from the realm of
geopolitics to the realm of daily life.
Maybe interpersonal life, maybe office
life, maybe career. All of that is very
much applicable. Sports, corporate life,
everything.
Rishi Maurya 20 Well, thank you so much.
Thank you so much. I was wondering
what's the question. Well, thank you
very much. I really appreciate your uh
support. Thank you.
Nikhil Bansal says, your channel's reach
is dropping due to current approach, not
any
whatever. Continuous live streams hurt
reach. Go back to focus videos as like
before I can reach will will help reach
on. Thank you very much for uh the
advice.
I am aware of the situation and I'm
aware of why my channel's reach is
capped is capped at
950,000.
Okay?
Uh
You can have your theories. I I have the
data. I have the statistics. I know when
it started.
When did my channel get capped? It got
capped March-April 2024, just before the
elections.
General elections.
Okay. So, I I know what's happening. I
am not one to complain. I'm going to
continue.
I know exactly based on the data. But, I
really appreciate your concern and your
advice. Thank you very much, sir.
Appreciate that.
Jasdeep Saran, thank you very much.
Thank you for your support. Really
appreciate that.
Jayant Maddika, thank you very much.
Thank you once again. Appreciate it.
MK says, was Indians was India a
satellite state of the USSR and not
sovereign?
Um was India not sovereign? India was
indeed sovereign. But, India was very
much in the USSR's camp.
India was, you could say,
uh a junior partner of the USSR.
India was not non-sovereign.
We did not have
we had not lost, let's say. See, there
are what what are the different kinds of
sovereignty that you have?
Let's take the example of the nations
that make up the European Union.
Let's take the example of let's say
Germany.
To understand sovereignty.
Germany lacks territorial sovereignty
because its borders are open. It's part
of the EU. Secondly, it is under foreign
occupation. You you have US troops
permanently stationed in Germany. So,
Germany doesn't have territorial
sovereignty. Germany doesn't have
economic sovereignty because it has to
use the euro. It has given up its old
currency, the Deutschmark. Kind of It's
kind of a rebranded Deutschmark, but it
doesn't have it doesn't control its
currency. Thirdly, it doesn't have
legislative sovereignty
because the legislation is done from
Brussels. Right?
And so on. So, these are the different
ways of defining sovereignty. And India
had all those,
you know, India definitely was
sovereign. But, India was kind of a
junior partner
of the USSR.
Nikhil Bansal says,
why has the
Why has the best
had better technology R&D when compared
to India, China, etc.?
The West, the West. Okay. Is it
cultural? Is it economic? Is it
geopolitical? We are not close to
cutting edge. It's about standards.
It's It's It's about standards. It's not
cultural. It's not
You could say standards are part of your
culture.
See, India, let's take India versus the
US, for example. Two very extreme
examples. India, a case of ridiculously
low standards. The US, in the 1950s-60s,
a case of ridiculously high standards.
So,
the US,
it's a nation that is based on cutthroat
competition.
It's a purely capitalistic nation. If
you are excellent, you will do excellent
and you will become a millionaire and
now a billionaire, trillionaire,
whatever. If you are mediocre, if you
are not competent, you're going to
struggle to put food on your on your
family's table, even if you work three
jobs in a day. Right? So, that's the
kind of nation the US is. Cutthroat
competition.
Purely based on merit for most people.
Right? And uh if you are good enough,
you are guaranteed to rise. The
The The society will take care of you.
Um
And they want to maximize their chances
of success and victory. It's an empire.
And uh they are aligned as an empire and
the education system uh
is entirely geared towards research and
developments and science and science and
technology. And that's why you had this
incredible excellence that the US
demonstrated in the 1950s and 1960s. It
It all started slowly declining after
'71.
Right?
So, it's because they had the highest
standards. The leaders they had
excellent leaders.
All all the way from top to bottom, at
least until the 1960s.
Right?
So, that's that's why the US is was
excellent. And and their entire
education system, especially in science
and technology, is entirely focused on
research, on actual research and
development, not on theory blah blah
blah Not that. Actual research
and development.
In India, you had the exact entirely
opposite situation. 1947, we There was a
transfer of power from one set of crooks
to another.
The system never changed. The British
system still continues today. Nothing
has changed. That system was designed to
exploit the country.
And only the top leadership has changed
after '47.
So, the exploitation the system of
exploitation continued. It still
exploits people.
It's a rent-seeking system.
It doesn't seek any progress. Look at
the universities.
They are designed Who are the
stakeholders in the education system?
It's supposed to be the students and the
country, right? But in the But the way
the education system functions, the
stakeholders are your professors, your
teachers, your staff,
your peons, your clerks.
Ask yourself one question. If a student
misbehaves, what happens? Tremendous
punishment. If a clerk misbehaves If If
a teacher misbehaves, what happens?
Nothing happens. Who's the real
stakeholder? Who's being protected?
So, the system is supposed to do one
thing, it does the opposite.
Horrific low standards all across across
the entire board in India.
It's not culture. Our culture is very
different. Our culture came back from
10,000 years ago. It was a It was a
culture of excellence. Now it is We are
losing the culture, right? We are being
denationalized.
It is not the culture. It's the system.
The system is designed
to destroy the country. Do you
understand the system is designed to
keep the country mediocre and destroy
it, erode it from within.
We are not close to cutting edge because
we are if the system is designed
to keep us as far from cutting edge as
possible. When you just don't do any
research and development, what cutting
edge will you do?
When the best When you When the mark of
excellence is how many mediocre papers
you publish in some third-rate journal,
what excellence will you have?
Would you like to see an example of a
journal of of a paper that is that is
published?
Uh what was it?
I had put this out yesterday. What was
it called?
Uh slavery, yeah.
Slavery in ancient
India, Pramod
Kumar.
Okay? Let's Let's take a look at at at
this paper.
I mean, look. Not this one.
Uh I think it's over here.
I mean, look at the quality of this
paper.
Good God.
This paper is written in such an abysmal
manner.
I mean, is this how you write a research
paper?
Utter utter mediocrity.
If you want to be a Hinduphobe, at least
do that with certain with a certain set
of with a certain minimum quality,
right?
So, this is the deal in India.
The nation of incredibly mediocre
standards because the system has imposed
this mediocrity on us.
That's the reason.
Okay, pretty long answer.
Sharan says, "Hi sir, thank you for all
the knowledge over the years." Thank you
very much, sir. Been a follower since
2020. Thank you very much. Thank you
very much.
Also, your French and Italian accents
are spot-on.
Thank you very much once again. Thank
you, sir.
Achintya Anand is a new member. Thank
you very much.
Very much so. Thank you.
Project Smiling Buddha says, "Happy
Diwali, sir, and everyone." Happy Diwali
to you as well and everyone
as well. Thank you very much.
Pratardan says, "Indians and West made
fun make fun of China for reverse
engineering Western technology. Do we
not realize that the West has done the
same from Germany and earlier India?"
That's what people don't realize.
It's not a mark of of inferiority
if you are able to successfully reverse
engineer technology. You need to have a
certain amount of competence to be able
to even reverse engineer something.
You are absolutely correct. What was
Operation Paperclip?
Operation Paperclip, which was conducted
by the United States. It was the
large-scale importation of rocket
engineers and scientists from Nazi
Germany who were spared any punishment
as long as they worked for the United
States.
And that is how the United States
created its space program.
They had no space program of their own.
They brought in
plane loads of of German engineers who
had worked on the cruise missiles and
and ballistic missiles for Nazi Germany.
See, Nazi Germany was the originator of
the cruise missile and the ballistic
missile.
The V1, V2, etc. rockets.
And those
Whatever Whichever rockets survived the
Whichever missiles survived, those were
shipped to the US. Those were
disassembled and and the
and reverse engineered. And the German
scientists and rocket engineers, etc.
They started building a more advanced
versions iteratively of those missiles.
And that's how the US,
you know,
space program was developed. And the
head of the US space program, the head
of NASA, was Wernher von Braun.
German. Nazi.
Right?
And the same goes for the jet engine and
so on, which also was pioneered by by
Nazi scientists.
So, that's how you do it.
That's how you do it. There is
absolutely nothing wrong with that. The
Chinese have reverse engineered
everything they could get their hands
on, and I really well
admire what they have achieved.
Why couldn't we reverse engineer
anything?
Because we didn't want to. We didn't
care care to do that. Our leaders wanted
allegedly kickbacks for buying weapons
from other countries, allegedly.
And that's why we The Once again, the
system is the problem. The system. The
system is designed to keep India
mediocre.
When you have
When you have an academic system
which doesn't care about about
about research and development, R&D,
then how will you reverse engineer
anything?
When your top professors are just
eminent scientists who have done nothing
actually in life and who can't reverse
engineer anything, who don't really know
how to do actually so something with
their own hands,
all they know is how to give lectures,
then what will you achieve?
When your education system is geared in
such a way It's It's constructed in such
a way that the most mediocre rise to the
top and the talent is destroyed, what
are you going to have?
That's the deal. That's the problem with
India. And that problem exists today.
It is even worse today.
That's the problem.
Nikhil Bansal says, "How do people in
regions rise to power?"
How do people in regions How do people
generally rise to power rise in power
rise to power? Well, if it's a political
system, if you will rise to political
power, you have to be politically
astute. And you typically have to rise
to power in the political party
somewhere.
And
so, you have to play the games of power.
You have to contribute. You have to be
very valuable to the party. If you're
valuable, then they will obviously
fast-track your promotion to higher and
higher positions. And then at the
highest position, if you want to get
elected, you have to be charismatic. You
have to be competent. You have to be
able to deliver on your promises and so
on. And that's how it's done. When you
have a different system, maybe
like in the past, then either you have
to be born in a royal family,
primogeniture, the firstborn son or the
most competent son,
or maybe you have to do a regime change
through
like Chandragupta did by overthrowing
the existing dynasty. And that sort of
thing. So, you know, different ways of
rising to power.
Prat DSP says, "What is Trump up to?
His king post literally over
the US people is a shame. Millions
protesting. Do you think things will get
worse in the US and the world?"
Well, Trump is here to stay for the next
three and a half years. So, yeah, I saw
his post.
So, in this post that he put out on
whatever
Truth Social or whatever it is,
so, it's a AI-generated post
in which there are there some protest of
some no kings protest that's happening
on the streets of some city in the US.
And Trump goes up in an in a fighter
plane in a fighter jet. He's wearing a
crown. Obviously, he sees himself as a
king as an emperor or something. And
from his aircraft, he drops
tons of on the people. Trump
seems to have a
fetish or something.
I don't know. He seems to have a great
fondness for excreta for excrement.
Trump.
Um yeah, pretty distasteful
post. Uh completely unbecoming of uh
a world leader, of the president of a
powerful nation, or any civilized
person. But it is what it is. That's
what you have in the US today.
You have Donald Trump.
Look,
Trump does have
some redeeming qualities, you know?
And overall, maybe he's going to make
things good for his Make Make Make life
better for his country, possibly. He's
going to ensure that that his nation
remains the most powerful nation, maybe
becomes even more powerful, and so on.
Yeah, clearly. So,
you know, at the end of the day, it
doesn't really matter
what you do in See, I've always said
this. I I think it was in 19 No, it was
not 19. It was in 2018 or 2019 that I
gave us
a talk
called the Turkish origins of India's
partition or something like that.
In which I spoke about Mustafa Kemal
Atatürk.
And Mustafa Kemal I said that Mustafa
Kemal Atatürk was one of the greatest
uh warriors, generals of all time and a
fantastic leader of Turkey.
The The essentially the founder of
modern modern Turkey.
He saved Turkey from annihilation
and he was the dictator for
uh for several years until he died of
liver cirrhosis because of
over-drinking. And I said that a leader
should be judged only
based on
what he contributes to his nation.
His personal life
doesn't matter. You should not be based
on your personal life. So, Atatürk was a
womanizer, he was a drunkard, he was not
a nice person at all as in person.
But he saved his country and he did so
much so much good for his country. So,
my point was that as a you should base
you should you should judge a leader
only based on their public life and what
they have contributed to their country
or if they have
committed any harm to their country.
Their personal life, if they are a nasty
person person doesn't matter. You may be
a womanizer, you may be drunkard, it
doesn't matter. He was still in my book
a great leader.
Right?
Uh so, it doesn't really matter.
So, Trump may have his eccentricities
and all, but as long as he makes the US
more powerful, I would say he's still a
great leader for his country.
That's how it goes. Okay?
Okay.
Pamshikha Lim says, "IAF's TVR
69.4 overtook PLAAF 63.8. IAF number
three, China number four. I don't care."
All these
rankings and all, look, anybody can put
out rankings.
I don't know what TVR means. I'm
expecting you're putting out some some
ranking of these the Indian Air Force,
the People's Liberation Army Air Force
and so on.
I would say the people the Chinese Air
Force is far more powerful than Indian
Indian Air Force. I don't know who came
came up with these rankings
and what's the what's the basis of how
they have calculated this. How did they
calculate? I'm not sure.
I would say the
the Chinese Air Force is more powerful
than the Indian Air Force. Look at the
rate at which they're churning out
aircraft.
Look at how many aircraft they have in
total.
Yeah, they are they're
They They are you know they're stuck in
various places and that's why they have
to they have to deploy aircraft in
various parts of their territory of
their country and they can't focus them
all against India, but still the
the Chinese Air Force is definitely more
powerful than the Indian
than the Indian Air Force. They produce
their own fighter planes in-house. We
import fighter planes. We have the Tejas
which we are still iteratively
developing. Fantastic that we have the
Tejas, but we don't have our own jet
engines.
We have so many issues.
What's the numbers that we have? We have
a huge shortfall of squadrons like they
say.
I I would not
consider the Indian Air Force to be in
the same league as the Chinese Air
Force. We are definitely better than the
Pakistani Air Force and whatever else.
Um
And the great saving grace that we have
is we have rightfully good missiles.
So, that that is an advantage we have,
but overall fighter planes and all I I
would say the Chinese Air Force is
better than the Indian Air Force. I'm
not being anti-national here. I'm being
completely transparent, honest, and
pragmatic, and practical over here.
Bhaskar says, "TikTok uses Oracle
service, why? What service should I
should I use for hosting my app? I don't
want to host on US servers.
Also, your views on Jio Black BlackRock
venture." I haven't looked into the Jio
BlackRock venture, so I would not be
able to comment about that.
Uh TikTok uses Oracle servers, why?
Because Oracle servers are the best in
the world. If you want to or if you need
to host your apps in you need a back
end, you need servers, you should go for
the best and most reliable servers that
are available to you.
Right?
That's what you should do.
Does Is there any Indian company that
offers you world-class servers a
world-class back end service?
If that doesn't exist, I I personally am
not aware of any.
I am aware of various US solutions.
There's Supabase which is like a
beginner's thing, but it can you can
scale it up, I suppose, to millions of
users.
And you obviously can use Oracle servers
servers.
My advice to you would be
use the best service that your money can
buy.
The best quality. The best uptime. The
best response times. The best SLAs,
whatever. That's what you should do.
Okay?
Um that's what I would say.
Uh And why does TikTok use that? Because
it's the best that's available.
Oracle is the best service, I suppose,
that's available.
Prachit Agarwal becomes a new member.
Thank you very much, Prachit. Appreciate
it very much. Thank you.
Aries Mantikor is a member for 20
months. Thank you so much. Thank you so
much. Thank you. We will keep on raising
our standards. Please do. Please do. It
will definitely have an effect on the
nation if we all do whatever we can in a
personal capacity to become better
versions of ourselves.
Thank you very much, sir. Thank you.
Project Smiling Buddha says, "Why do
some Indians believe that some foreign
E2E encrypted app is safe? Why so naive?
The West has been snooping on on all on
all private messages. Just Google
Snapchat Indian chat splay Spain plane
Taliban just one example. Let us Google
it. Let us Google it."
Okay, Snapchat.
Snapchat
Indian chat
uh spay spay Spain
plane Taliban. What is this?
A British Indian student Aditya Verma is
on trial in Spain for a Snapchat message
he sent while in an airport
before a flight to Spain. In a message
to friends he jokingly wrote, "On my way
to blow up the plane. I'm a member of
the Taliban." And this message was
detected by UK authorities. It triggered
the Spanish Air Force to scramble
fighter jets to escort his flight.
This was in 2022. And the Spanish
scrambled to F-18 fighter jets to flank
the aircraft. It was made to land in
Menorca where this very brilliant person
was arrested.
And he said it was a joke. I'm sure it
was a joke because Indians the worst
they will do is joke. They will never do
such a thing.
So, it's clear. Look, if you imagine
that your
that your messages and your data is is
is private,
you are super deluded.
You're super delusional. Nothing is
private.
If you are a person of interest,
they're going to snoop on you. Whatever
messages you're you're sending through
your favorite messaging application,
they'll be snooped up they'll be
accessible to whoever is snooping.
Especially foreign governments, possibly
even your own government, whoever you
are.
So,
Indians Indians are well, Indians are
super naive, right? Indians are super
naive, unfortunately. What can I say?
They believe that encryption ensures
that they believe that laws are you
know, laws actually matter.
Uh why why are we so naive? Because
because of the well, it all goes back to
the education system. You we are not
taught how to think critically.
We
imagine that the we we we imagine I
don't know what. It's
basically it's because Indians are not
taught how to think critically and
that's why they they are so easy to
fool. That's the That's the whole thing.
That's the That's the root cause of
everything. No ability to think
critically. Uh they believe what people
in authority tell them. Indians are
incredibly deferential to authority
figures. Incredibly deferential. If If
you're a person in authority, if you're
an eminent person, if you are especially
a person with white skin, people Indians
will like, "Oh, sir. Yes, sir. We
believe you."
So, that's the problem.
Very naive people. I don't know what to
do to change this. I don't know.
Aman says, "Is world government a
possibility? What are your thoughts on a
universal basic income?"
I think a world government, if it
happens, will happen through the back
door.
It will happen How So, how can you have
a world government that happens through
through the back door?
A world government becoming a reality
through the back door means that the
world will keep on imagine continue to
imagine that you have governments
everywhere which are independent.
Like the people of Japan imagine that
Japan is an independent country.
Like the people of Germany imagine
Germany is independent.
Like the people of Korea imagine that
they have democracy, they have a
government, and the government decides
what happens in the country. Right?
Most people in these countries believe
that they genuinely are a democracy and
an independent sovereign nation.
So, imagine the same situation happens
to the rest of the world to the entirety
of the entirety of the world. And
the majority of the people continue to
believe that you know, because we have
elections, I go and vote every four
years, I go and vote every five years.
You have government that come and go.
You have leaders that that are sometimes
in power and sometimes they are voted
out of power. Look, we have a
functioning democracy. We have we have a
military.
We have sovereignty.
But what if all your leaders all your
entire system is just a show? It's just
a sham. Like you have in Japan.
Like you have in Korea South Korea.
Right? Like you have in the EU nations.
I think now it's becoming apparent to
the people of the EU that it's a sham,
but you know,
still the majority still believe, I
suppose.
So, if you What if you install a system
in every country that's like a
plug-and-play system?
Ideally, a democratic system where you
have voting.
Okay?
So, you have election this electoral
cycle that happens.
Your prime minister president comes and
goes, is there for a few years, then
somebody else comes in. You have various
political parties.
But what if everybody actually serves
some foreign master?
And they're all just playing a game.
Their pockets are being lined. What
about that? Then you have a world
government by proxy and nobody ever
realizes this. So, it is certainly a
possibility. I think it will it is more
likely to happen through the back door
than overtly world government, which
will scare everybody.
But what if you keep people living in
Lala Land?
Get people addicted to scrolling reels
all day.
Yeah. Get get people influenced by
various influencers.
Put across the message, the right
messages.
Yeah, so it's very much a possibility.
So, to some extent the world government
has happened in in Europe, EU, in the
West.
Maybe it will spread out to other
countries, possibly.
What are my thoughts on UBI? Universal
basic income, I think it's a very bad
idea.
It me It will make people complacent. It
will It will destroy human productivity,
you know, creativity, all of that.
If you are guaranteed an income,
then why will you work?
Unless you are a you are driven from
within, which is very which is like 0.1%
of the people.
99.9% of the people, if you give them a
decent income,
and you give them entertainment, you
give them a PS PS5 or Xbox, you give
them a phone with
with cheap internet,
you give them home delivery food, that's
it. What else do you want? Life is done.
Life is good.
Yeah?
It's like the Matrix. I think it's a
very bad idea.
Uh
So, you have the concept of what? Social
security in some countries, right? If
you are jobless and all, the government
will give will give you some some money
until you get a job and so on.
Uh I think social security to some
extent makes sense, but every giving
everybody UBI,
I think it's a bad idea.
Animesh says, "The hegemonic empire will
surmount more pressure in and around
India in the times to come.
How does India weather the storm and and
still sustainably grow?"
Yes, the empire will certainly apply
more pressure on India. That is
obviously in the empire's interests.
Right? Uh they would like to have a
bipolar world order. One is the US-led
Western-led world order, and the second
is the Russia-China world order in case
the two nations continue to stay
together.
And they want the entire world to make a
choice. You are either here or there.
They don't want the multipolar world
order, which is kind of a mess. They
want to go back to the 20th century kind
of situation when you had a where you
had a bipolar world.
And India is one of the major pieces on
the chessboard, and they would like to
have India on their side. So, if the
current government is being problematic
and insisting on India's sovereignty,
then maybe they would like to install
somebody else
in the top job in Delhi who will be more
pliable.
So, pressure will increase on India in
in a variety of ways.
So, how do you install
a different person in power?
By making the current person in power
look in you know, incompetent, you know,
weak, helpless, and so on. By creating
all kinds of
pressure points and executing those.
Uh so, how does India weather the storm
and still sustainably grow?
We will have to look for other allies.
India India seems to have, you know,
calculated that we need to put all our
all our eggs in the Western basket.
Or much much of our eggs in the Western
market baskets. Our foreign policy to
some extent has kind of been reactive
for a while.
Not completely reactive, of course. We
are taking initiative, but you can see
that
still see that the initiatives we're
taking in the foreign policy realm are
kind of reactions to what's happening to
us.
Reactions.
So, we need to be more proactive. We
need to have our own clear agenda. We
need to have our aims and objectives for
2050 or whatever. And we need to take
care of the economy.
If we can't if we are being you know,
we need to have
various trade agreements, free trade
agreements, etc. with as many nations
and economic groups as economic blocks
as possible. We just did that with the
UK recently. We have something going on
with the with the Australians as well.
Uh it doesn't look like there's going to
be something happening anytime soon with
the Americans, but because the Americans
want, well, complete access to the
Indian economy without any tariff, which
obviously is a will be a disaster if we
if we accept that.
So, uh
maybe we should become a
consumption-driven economy, which for
which we will need way more reforms than
we have right now. So, we're going to
have to find solutions
to the existing problems. We're going to
have to align or or let's say partner
with as many nations and economic groups
as possible.
And we need to we will need to become
more agile diplomatically and in other
ways as well. So, all that needs to
happen.
Biju says, "In geopolitical terms, how
much influential is the geographical
location of a country? How much does it
affect the fortunes of a country? How
would you rate India's location What are
top five?"
Let's look at the map of the world. The
The number one
best geographic location is the United
States. Let me explain why.
Look at the United States.
To its east, it has the Atlantic Ocean.
If someone wants to invade the US, they
have to cross the Atlantic Ocean. Not
going to happen. I mean, extremely
difficult.
To the west, they have the Pacific
Ocean, and even wider stretch of land.
You want to invade the US, you're going
to have to cross the Pacific Ocean. Very
difficult. To the north, you have a
south state, Canada, which doesn't
matter at all, completely insignificant
nation in all ways.
In every way. To the south, you have
another vassal state, unfortunately,
Mexico, which used to be a civilization
once upon a time. It's no longer that.
So, the US And And if you look at the
southern American nations in South
America, all
all are entirely aligned with the US,
except for one nation, Venezuela, which
I'm sure they will take care of very
soon.
Very soon, it looks like there'll be a
regime change in in Venezuela.
So, the entirety of the of the Americas
is controlled by the US.
So, there is no threat the US faces. And
if you look at the US, it's just it's a
continent-sized nation.
A complete autarky. Everything that you
need is available. All the resources you
need are available in the US. And
they've
they've tremendous access to the world's
oceans on both sides. Brilliant
geographic location. What else can you
ask for? Right?
Uh that's number one. I'm in top five, I
don't know. India has a great location.
We dominate the Indian Ocean region.
Apart from the US, no other nation
dominates a body of water,
a major ocean like we do, right?
Uh
we have all every possible terrain you
can imagine, every possible climate you
can imagine, from Arctic climate to
super tropical climate. We have
archipelagos, we have islands, we have
volcanoes, we have the tallest
mountains, we have deserts, we have
snows, we have valleys. We have
everything. Of course, the neighbors
aren't great, but that's because of our
own weakness.
So, geographically, we are we are
fantastically located.
Uh the Chinese have good advantages. The
Russians have tremendous advantages. So,
overall, the the geographical location
of a country is super influential in
shaping the nation's fortunes. That's
that's
very important, for sure.
Um Chat DSP says, "Asif Munir did the
nuclear rant again. What is the red line
India should be wary of where the US
permits the use of nukes?
Would the Pakistan disintegration can be
one?
Could India advance
Indian advance be another? Or no red
lines whatsoever?"
Um what Okay, so what is the red line
if which if crossed will result in the
Americans
permitting Pakistan to use nuclear
weapons against India?
I think it would be the disintegration
of Pakistan.
Uh let's let's
think about it.
Uh
Pakistani disintegration would
definitely be a red line that the
Americans would be okay with Pakistan
using nuclear weapons.
Um Indian advance into Pakistan, which
would take out big chunks of Pakistani
Pakistani occupied territory, would be
another,
I suppose. I think if India takes back
POK, it may not quite be a red line.
Especially if it done so if it is done
so fast that no one has any time to
react. If we take three weeks to take
back POK, you you may have
the possibility of nuclear weapons used.
But if we take it in 24 hours to 48
hours, so fast that, you know,
in a blink of an eye,
then it's a fait accompli. It's done.
Then what? Then there is no chance of a
nuclear use, right? So, if we take
territory
super fast, lightning fast, then there
is less of a chance of nuclear weapons
use.
So, you take territory rapidly, then you
stop.
Then you unilaterally declare a
ceasefire. Well, then
there's no other, you know, then then
how do you use nukes when there's a
ceasefire in operation unilaterally?
So, if you do a pulse-pause kind of war,
you rapidly advance, take big big chunk
of territory, then you
unilaterally stop. Then there's
very little chance of nuclear weapons
use.
So, I would say that nuclear weapons
could be used if India takes a very long
time time to to take territory, huffing,
puffing along slowly, slowly. That that
is a very bad, you know,
approach. Secondly, if the if the
Pakistani nation itself is on the brink
of disintegrating, the US could
potentially permit the Pakistanis to use
those nuclear weapons.
Um
So, it depends. If India advances
advances on Lahore or Islamabad, that
could be possibly
a red line.
So, I'm just speculating here, okay? I'm
not
aware of what the actual red lines are
if they do exist. Uh but one thing is
certain, if the Pakistanis use a nuclear
weapon against us, their nation is going
to be vaporized. That is a guarantee.
So, if the Americans do issue the order
to Pakistan to
use nuclear weapons, it will most likely
be
you know, major cities will be targeted
in India. Maybe Delhi, maybe something
else.
The objective will be to to launch a
decapitation strike on India. That's
That's essentially what they will try
because they know that if they use
nukes,
they're going to be vaporized. So, then
if they use nukes, they should do as
much damage as possible before before
being vaporized.
So, it's going to be that sort of thing.
If it ever happens. One hopes One hopes
it never happens.
Pakistan needs to disintegrate. It's
It's an artificial temporary terrorist
nation.
Um yeah, so that's the kind of scenarios
we can one can think of.
Bijoy says Diwali ki shubhkamnaye. Thank
you very much. Apko bhi Diwali ki
shubhkamnaye. Thank you very much.
Pratik says, I think Trump is going to
be another JFK.
Okay.
All right, sir.
Ushant Singh says, can India achieve
rapid state transformation and economic
self-reliance while maintaining
democracy or does breaking colonial
bureaucratic structures require
authoritarian methods like Stalin's
USSR?
That's a very impressive question you're
asking. You can't
achieve rapid transformation while
maintaining this this current form of
democracy. No, not possible.
The current form of democracy is
actually a form of super mediocrity.
You can have democracy while having
rapid transformation, but that has to be
a very centralized form of democracy.
A very strong power structure in India.
We have a very loose power structure.
The Prime Minister doesn't have a lot of
power in India.
The states are super powerful.
There are so many
uh things that are state subjects. Law
and order is a state issue. The center
has to stay stay out of it and so on.
Uh that's one example. There are so many
things that are like state issues and
the center has to stay out of those
things. So, India is a very very weak
democracy.
Um
very weak
The center doesn't have sufficient power
to really,
you know, push across changes and
reforms in the country. So, if we want
rapid transformation, economic
self-reliance, and all those things,
we will have to change the entire system
of governance
of India, which will necessarily will
require, if you want to do it rapidly,
pretty authoritarian methods,
right?
If you want to
dismantle the colonial system which
still exists,
you're going to have to go up against
everybody who benefits from the colonial
system,
which is all
essentially, well,
people who are part of the governance
machinery.
It will also include the politicians. It
will also include the education system,
the the people who benefit from that,
the super mediocrities.
It'll
essentially
you will need a revolution for that to
happen.
Because so many people who are
entrenched in power,
they benefit from the system. Millions
of these people, they benefit from the
system, which keeps India down.
Yeah?
Big ask.
SS Phoenix says, it'll be useful to
cover Mackinder's Eurasian Heartland
theory. I have covered that. Just Google
Just See, I'll show you. I'll show you
how to do it.
Yeah?
So, let's go to Google.
Um one second.
I'll I'll show you
what I mean by that.
Uh
share screen. Okay, let me go to Google.
All right. Let's go to my YouTube
channel.
Okay, we go to my YouTube channel, all
right? And then,
if you go to my channel, there must be a
search box here.
Mackinder.
So, there's at least one question over
here that I would rest. Maybe it's in
this episode 103.
Um so, I have
definitely covered this in the past.
Uh
maybe it would be beneficial for me to
make a separate video about that.
Uh
I'm sure
I agree with you that very few Indians
are aware
of the Eurasian Heartland theory.
So, what is the What is Mackinder's
theory?
It says that there is It introduces the
concept of something called the world
island.
Okay?
And it says that to control the world,
you have to control the world island,
and to control the world island, you
have to control the heartland of the
world island. What is the heartland? It
is essentially the heart of Eurasia,
which is present-day Russia.
And it says that to control Russia
Russia,
the the the
the pathway to controlling Russia is
through what is currently
called Ukraine. So, the Ukraine war is
essentially that,
you know? And there is something called
the rimland nations. India is a rimland
nation. It says rimland nations can
never be world leaders. It's always the
heartland nations that can be world
leaders. And
to to control the entire world, if the
US wants to control the entire world, it
has to control the region which is
currently called which is which is
Russia, the heartland of Eurasia.
That essentially in in a very very
small nutshell is Mackinder's Eurasian
Heartland theory. You can obviously
expand it in great detail. Um so, that's
what it is. Now,
SS Phoenix says that very few Indians
Americans populists are aware of
design, but the British establishment
foment war, suppress civilizations, and
realize the new world order.
Um
Is it the British establishment? Is it
the Western establishment? Whatever you
want to call it.
Um
Suppressing civilizations is something
that definitely is on the agenda. And
that's why they're specifically going
after India because India still is kind
of
still an existing old civilization.
Uh the Chinese
Chinese also, you could say to some
extent, are a civilization. Both India
and China are kind of in the same boat.
Uh the Chinese are more more in line
with their civilizational heritage
because they write Chinese, they speak
Chinese, the Chinese language is the
medium of instruction in schools,
colleges, universities. They eat with
chopsticks. Uh they don't worship the
West. They don't have an inferiority
complex.
Right? All of that is there. India is
the complete opposite, a slave-minded
nation,
a nation that is saddled with mental
colonization. So, China is ahead of
India, but India still is
The Chinese have become a communist
nation, so they've kind of
set aside their culture beyond what I
just said.
They no longer worship the old gods and
all that, the gods that their ancestors
worshipped. They have a totally
different atheistic system.
India to some extent still is more in
line with its culture. So, very
Yeah, different
forms of deracination that we see in
these two old civilizations. And that's
why they would like to disestablish
these two civilizations in different
ways, suppress civilizations.
Uh realize the new world order, which is
a one world government either overtly or
by from the back door, etc. Yeah.
Yeah, so I I agree. It's useful to to
cover this topic in in more detail.
Maybe I Maybe I can do that.
So, thank you for the recommendation and
suggestion. Thank you, sir.
All right. Uh Utyos says, maybe 6-hour
episode on 300. What are my thoughts?
Mm.
So, recently a a few like a couple of
months ago, I did an 8-hour episode, Ask
Abhijit.
And I was personally super surprised
that I was able to do that without any
ill effects.
I At the end,
I I It was It actually ended up being
being an 8-hour 45-minute episode,
almost 9 hours. And by the end of the
episode, I was wondering, will will I be
able to speak tomorrow? But I I turned
out to be okay. So, looks like I have
the vocal and physical stamina to sit
for 8 hours and speak.
Yeah, so
is that something you all would like to
This is episode 298. We're So, next
weekend, Sunday, should be episode 300.
Would you like me to do a long episode
to celebrate number 300, triple century?
6 hours, maybe longer. What What What do
you all say?
Maybe I'll put a poll on the community
page,
and you all can vote on it. If it's
something you would like me to do, I'll
be happy to do it.
Yeah? 300 episodes is I would say not a
small achievement. That's That's quite a
number.
Yeah. So, yeah, I'll be happy to
to do something like that.
If If everyone wants that. Yeah? If it's
something that's
there by popular demand, I'll be very
happy to do that. So, thank you for the
suggestion. Let me know.
Um I'll put out a poll so that we can
have actual numbers and people can vote
on that.
Uh Prasun
Medhekar says, what should India do if
Pakistan invades Afghanistan?
If Pakistan decides to invade
Afghanistan, they'll be in deep deep
trouble. But what should India do?
India should supply a certain weapon
systems to Afghanistan.
Uh if the Pakistanis are conducting air
strikes in Afghanistan, they should
supply the the Akash system to
Afghanistan, which is the world's best
battle-tested air defense system,
anti-air defense you know system.
Um
It it
it was battle-tested during operation
Sindoor and it took everything out.
Uh so we should maybe help Afghanistan
with that. Maybe supply some Akash
systems to Afghanistan. And maybe we
should supply some BrahMos batteries to
Afghanistan. You know, something like
that.
All right.
Ah.
Sir James
Rabbi Mizrachi Mizra Okay, calls Hindus
something worshipers.
Um even the Jew can't stand him. There's
a reason Churchill warned warned us
about you.
Okay, I am not entirely sure about who
Rabbi Mizrachi is
and what he calls Hindus.
Um
Yeah, so I am not sure I can comment
about this because I'm not aware of the
of the context and the background, but
uh James, it is always good to have your
questions on
on the Ask Abhijit show. I I appreciate
you, sir. Thank you.
I do.
ICMB says uh is India doing enough to
build a leverage and influence in
resource-rich African economies through
digital infrastructure like UPI
and other services?
Well, if you ask me personally and
everything is obviously here personally.
I would say we are not doing enough.
I think there is there is still much
more that we can do.
You know, to partner with various
African
economies. Obviously, there is already
competition in Africa. I mean tremendous
competition. On the one hand, the
Chinese First of all, Africa was
colonized by the Europeans in the 1800s
and many even before that to some
extent.
And it was completely destroyed
by the 1950s and 1960s. And then the
Europeans like
kind of left Africa. Addio Africa. Sort
of. Addio Africa.
But movie recommendation. Not I mean
very interesting movie.
But uh
you have to you know, have a little bit
of a stout temperament to watch it. It's
called Africa Addio.
I'm sure it's available on YouTube.
Is it?
Africa Addio. Uh it's it's not it's it's
not for the faint of heart first of all.
Trailer.
I think it's available on YouTube. The
entire movie. Various versions of the
movie are available.
And it's it's about the time when you
the Europeans were you know, moving out
of Africa.
And Africa was African various African
countries were kind of being given
independence even though you had
dictators running the country and that
sort of thing.
Uh so Africa was destroyed by the
Europeans and then after the 1950s and
60s, they continued
ruling Africa and extracting resources
of resources out of Africa through proxy
dictatorships and so on.
Um
And then the Chinese started you know,
making their presence felt in Africa and
partnering with various African
countries
through various means to extract
resources. Now the Russians are also
involved in the in the Sahel region. So
it's Russian muscle, Chinese money, that
sort of thing which is up against the US
old establishment US led old
establishment. The French have withdrawn
from Africa. I think there is
significant scope for India to get more
involved than what it is right now.
India is hardly involved in Africa right
now. We have good relations with a lot
of African nations.
We have done nice things for Africa. For
example,
um
in 2023 when we had the G20 summit in
Delhi, we
made the African Union a member of the
G20. So it's not the G20 one
essentially. So all those things we've
done, but we need to do more
beyond these symbolic gestures. We need
to do more.
You know, so I think India is right now
not
quite doing enough
to build leverage and influence in
various African countries.
Um
Through a variety of means. We should we
can certainly do much more. Yeah.
Shivansh says says happy Diwali
Dipawali. Thank you very much. Wish you
the same.
Indian scam centers have become a big
headache not only for us Indians, but
abroad too. Last year I was in Seoul,
South Korea and all that people were
asking us is why do so many scammers
originate in India? Is there nothing we
can do to cut down on this?
I don't know.
Scam centers. Well,
that's that's a stereotype that exists
about India, right? That India is
home to scammers
scam call centers and so on.
Um
Is it that big of a problem? I am
personally not aware of this. In case it
is,
then and and in case it's a nuisance and
it in case it is something that is
uh
creating a bad image of India
internationally, then maybe the
government of India should pass some
laws that makes you know,
any kind of scam illegal in case those
laws don't exist.
I mean
anything that is considered a scam is
obviously illegal, right? Scam Scam
means you're doing something illegal.
You're you're fleecing someone. You're
you're you're stealing the money or
whatever.
Misrepresenting things and so on.
Um
So uh
yeah, in case this is a big problem or
even if it's a medium problem or small
problem, I think uh
uh I mean I suppose laws would exist in
India to to
criminalize any scam-like activity.
In case such laws So I have not looked
into this.
It's all about Even if laws exist, if
you don't enforce the laws, then what's
the point, right?
So yeah, I think India needs to crack
down on on these things because it looks
like it looks like from what you're
saying South Korea
that a lot of people there seem to
regard India as a nation where a lot of
scammers originate.
Yeah, so maybe this should be needs to
be brought to the to the government of
India's notice.
Um and they need to crack down on these
people who are running such scams.
Definitely, it's a cause for concern.
Yeah.
Nikhil Bansal says how is Modi BJP
performance in geopolitics and why?
I would say it's the best performance of
all the governments thus far.
Okay.
Uh how many go See, what are the major
regimes that we've had in India since
dominion status, which is 1947?
So 1947 we get dominion status. 1950 or
somewhere somewhere around that time we
become a republic. Around that time we
have the Nehruvian regime that goes on
until the 1960s. Then we have Lal
Bahadur Shastri. Then we have
Mrs. Gandhi.
Then you have
briefly Mr. Morarji Desai. Then Mrs.
Gandhi back again. Then she is
assassinated sadly. Then Rajiv Gandhi
comes to power. Then
then you have like three then you have
this period of
of uh
it unstability instability in in
politics. You have like
multiple governments Chandra Shekhar, VP
Singh, HD Deve Gowda, etc. that come and
go come and go come and go. Then you
have Narasimha Rao Narasimha Rao who
last lasts 5 years. Then you have Mr.
Vajpayee Atal Bihari Vajpayee who who is
there for a while. Then he comes back
and he completes his term. Then you have
Dr. Manmohan Singh and then you have
Mr. Modi.
If you look at all these governments, I
think Mr. Modi
and the BJP the from 2014 until now,
their performance in geopolitics has
been the most robust.
And
people will say what are you talking
about? The US has become an enemy.
The US treats India as an enemy today.
The US has a very adversarial approach
towards India.
During Dr. Manmohan Singh time Manmohan
Singh's time and in the during other
times, the US was so nice to India.
So nice to us.
They treated treated us so nicely.
And look at them now. They're treating
us like an adversary. Why is that? It's
precisely because the past 10 years
we've become more powerful.
We are no longer an irrelevant nation.
If you are irrelevant, the powerful
nations will treat you nicely.
At least
the words will be nice.
The actions will be benign neglect or
some sort of exploitation.
But the moment they you start rising and
growing as a genuine world power, that's
when they start looking at you
through an adversarial lens.
So the past 11 years India has become a
genuinely
powerful nation. It's one of the top
world powers. It's the fourth fourth
most powerful nation
overall in the world. Cumulative hard
power. India was nowhere 10 years ago.
Nowhere.
I would say the performance has been the
best
of all the Indian governments we've had.
So your performance in geopolitics is
entirely tied to your hard power. What
is how much hard power do you have? The
more hard power you have, the more
leverage you have in geopolitics.
So I would say it's the best go go
government we've had thus far.
Of course, they can do things better.
Much better.
No question about that. But still
overall, I would say it's the best we've
had.
Anonymous scientist, good to see you,
sir. Boswell, happy Choti Diwali.
Thank you. Same to you as well. Merci.
Uh was the October 7th attack uh carried
out to derail the IMEC and sabotage the
Abraham the Abraham Accords?
I
I can't say.
Uh See, this October 7th attack was
carried out by terrorists. By Hamas.
A heinous
terrorist organization.
And it was a heinous attack.
Now, why did a bunch of terrorists do
what they do? I think only terrorists
can understand.
Why did they choose that day? I suppose
they chose that day because it It the
50th anniversary of the Yom Kippur War.
Hm? Maybe it was that.
Like a day or give or take a day, right?
Um
So, the the Hamas don't care about the
IMEC.
Hamas only cares about being terrorist
and do whatever terrorists do. And Hamas
was aligned with Pakistan. The Hamas
supported Pakistani you know, terrorism
against India.
Uh so, I'm not sure if IMEC uh derailing
IMEC was part of the agenda.
Sabotaging the Abraham Accords, I'm not
sure. I don't really know what what was
going on in her the minds of the Hamas
leadership, but it was clearly suicidal.
So, I I'm not sure. I'm not sure what
was behind that. If it was done by an
actual nation, one could think about
what that nation wants. If you think
about Hamas as a terrorist organization,
all they want is the destruction of
Israel.
So, I would say they chose that day
because it coincided with roughly the
50th anniversary of that big of Israel's
biggest intelligence failure. Perhaps
that was the reason for that. And I'm
not sure if this had anything to do with
IMEC or the Abraham Accords.
Ritwik says,
uh why the US can regime change only in
poor democratic countries? The US can't
buy people in Iran or North Korea.
Hm Mr. Because Mr. Khamenei Mr. Kim will
immediately shoot them.
Is it a benefit of not having a
democracy? Look.
Look.
Let's say you have
all across the world the same system.
The same system, same democracy.
Same democratic system.
Plug and play.
So, then if you are the US,
you can
take out a leader and put another
leader, plug and play.
And in a couple of months, people will
say, "Okay, everything is back to
normal."
You understand?
Democracy
has That's the deal with democracy.
Democracy is not
well,
it's hardly democratic, actually. It's
it's it's an illusion of democracy.
There there can be no real democracy in
the world, actually. If you study what
democracy actually is.
And I'm not sure democracy is even the
best system ever
because it is the rule of the
It's ruled by by the mob.
See,
in any nation, in any society,
the progress of the society depends on
the top 0.1% of the people.
So,
maybe the Greeks were right when they
allowed only certain people to vote and
participate in democracy, which is like
1%.
Women were not allowed to vote. I'm not
against I'm not in favor of not allowing
women to vote. I'm completely in favor
of equality of genders, no question
about that. But the Greeks did not allow
women to vote. They did not allow slaves
to vote. A lot of people were slaves.
They did not allow peasants to vote.
Only the super rich and powerful people
who had a track record of achieving
things, they were allowed to vote.
That's was That was the kind of
democracy they had. But in a in a in the
modern democratic system, it is the rule
of the rabble.
The rabble isn't typically the most
intelligent, unfortunately, right?
So,
that has the the effect that, you know,
you often have very low-quality leaders
who come to power in various countries.
People who are charismatic but can't do
a thing. Who people who are great
talking and giving speeches but can't
really
make any good changes or or or govern
properly.
And then you can And when you have a
situation like that,
you can create these these fake
movements, you know, that people are
dissatisfied and they want a different
um leadership.
And then you can install NGOs in the
country
that astroturf movements
that create these fake grassroots
movements
and you can achieve regime change. And
then you just plug and play and change
the change the leader.
And in a couple of months, everything
goes back to normal and people will be
back to scrolling reels.
Opium of the masses.
So, that's why regime change can work
spectacularly in poor democratic
countries.
In democratic countries, even in rich
democratic countries, you can have that.
Look at the EU countries. They don't
even have democracy now.
They have the illusion of democracy.
But when it comes to Iran and North
Korea, well, you see, these are
dictatorial nations, even even China.
You could say
Yeah, let's let's stick to
China, Iran, North Korea. Yeah, they
will shoot anyone who tries to,
you know, rise up against the
government. So, that certainly is a
benefit of not having a democracy. Look,
what do people want?
What is it that human beings want in
life?
They want peace,
stability, prosperity,
good quality of life,
and great future for their children and
their descendants. That's all you want.
They don't care about democracy or
dictatorship. If you have a dictator who
provides all of this
and people are happy, they don't care.
So, the point is the system doesn't
matter.
What matters is the outcome for the
people.
It doesn't matter whether the cat is
black or white as long as it is it
catches mice.
Hm?
But the Americans, they've created this
illusion that only white cats work and
black cats are bad.
So, that's the mental conditioning that
we are that is imposed upon people.
Okay. Uh Lavanya Shaw says, "Will a gold
revaluation
happen in the US with with respect to
the dollar and then spread across the
countries and currencies? Your thoughts
on its on its effects? Happy Diwali
Dipawali. Happy Dipawali to you as well,
ma'am."
"Will a gold revaluation happen in the
US with respect to the dollar?" I doubt
it very much. Uh if you are talking
about
pegging the US to the to the
price of gold once again
pegging
pegging the US dollar to the price of
gold once again like it used to be
before the 1970s, I think that's very
unlikely.
Because
because look,
if you look at
what 1 kg of gold could buy you in let's
say 1950,
let's say it could buy you a nice big
house with X number of rooms and nice
walled garden around you.
Maybe let's say hypothetically, 1 kg of
gold could buy you that much in 1950 in
the US.
Well, I'll tell you what, 1 kg of gold
will buy you exactly the same thing
today in the US.
But 1 kg of gold, if it cost X dollars
in 1950, it will cost way more today.
So, the US dollar has lost a tremendous
amount of value today
compared to what
the value was what its value was in
1950. So, if you want to peg the the US
dollar to the price of gold today,
um
it will significantly devalue the US
dollar, right?
And if if if you want to peg every
currency in the world to the price of
gold once again,
then
all the currency rates and exchange
rates will go for a toss and they will
again
they they will change significantly.
And the US dollar may no longer have the
same value it has today and that will
not be good for the US. So, I think
that it is very unlikely the that the US
government will
peg the US dollar to the price of gold
once again. I don't think that's on the
cards. If it spreads to other countries
and currencies, it will completely
reconfigure
the exchange rates and completely
destabilize the global economy.
Right? So, I think it's it's pretty
unlikely to happen.
Happy Diwali.
Anonymous scientist says, "Donald J.
Trump has authorized regime change in
Venezuela and Machado has won the Nobel
Prize
for peace." Peace.
"Is the US desperate for oil to counter
cheap Russian supplies?" No.
The US is the world's largest
producer of oil in the world
today.
Um it's it's possibly one of the largest
exporters of oil as well in the world
today.
Uh what the US wants to do is they want
to control the entire supply
of oil across the world as much as as as
possible.
They want to control as much as possible
of the world's supply of oil.
So, Venezuela is a major oil exporting
nation. Let's quickly Google the top 10
ex- oil exporting nation oil producing
nations.
Top 10 oil
producing countries. Let's see.
So,
number one is the US. Oh, Venezuela
doesn't doesn't figure, does it? Doesn't
exist here, really.
Uh Venezuela.
Venezuela definitely is one of the Okay,
let's see here, Wikipedia. I'm not sure
if it's completely accurate, but let's
see.
US, Saudi Arabia, Russia, etc. etc.
Where is Venezuela? Venezuela is 19.
But it's still a major oil producer.
And
so, the US wants to wants to control
that.
Because
by doing so, they can well, they can
impose more pressure on various
countries.
And they can
Yeah, so so that gives them more control
over the over the world's oil supply.
So, um the US is not desperate for oil
to counter cheap Russian supplies. They
want to cut down all the non-Russian
um independent
uh sources of oil that nations have
access to.
So, there are various nations that are
independent but actually are controlled
by the US. So, they want to add one more
to the list so that they can So, the
more oil sources you can control, the
more you can
pressurize various countries. That
That's the whole point.
Uh so, it looks like a regime change
will happen in Venezuela sooner or
later. Maduro looks like unfortunately
his his days are numbered as the leader
of Venezuela.
And uh if a regime change happens, then
he will probably go to jail or something
worse will happen to him unless he can
go go into exile to some other country?
Machado, this lady who that nobody was
aware of, she is now a Nobel Prize
winner. And the first thing she does is
she goes on a podcast with
Donald J. Trump Donald Trump Don Donald
Trump Jr.
And she says, "Please take our oil.
When the regime change happens, we will
give you everything.
Your companies come can come and make
huge amounts of money."
That's what she's saying. She's
essentially
she can't wait to sell her country off
to the US.
So, the Nobel Prize for Peace has become
political prize. It's like a a
It's like the Magsaysay Award on
steroids.
So, generally see the Magsaysay Award in
the past used to be a pretty good award.
It was not political in the past, but in
recent times it's become a very
political award. Typically people who
Typically not always not always please
understand there are always exceptions.
Just to put it on the record. There are
always exceptions, but typically the
Magsaysay Award is given to people who
serve the US. It is given as
a prize for services rendered and a
prize that incentivizes more services in
the future.
So, people who serve the US
and not their country
typically not always are given the
Magsaysay Magsaysay prize.
And now it it has
It also clearly applies to the Nobel
Peace Prize also. So, that's the deal
now.
Ritwik says, "Geopolitical importance of
Argentina and Brazil. I mean they are
big countries. Are they sovereign or US
vassals? They have a great location
also."
What do you think?
The entirety of the Americas, whether
it's the continent of North America
or the continent of South America
entirely under US domination.
Apart from Venezuela which they will
deal with it looks like very soon and
Cuba.
Cuba they have allowed it to exist for
whatever reason as as an as a somewhat
anti-US nation.
Ideologically opposed to the US in the
in that sort of thing.
And they have completely beggarized
pauperized Cuba. Go to Cuba you will
realize what I mean.
Crumbling nation sadly.
Um
So, what's the geopolitical importance
of Argentina?
What can I say? I'm I'm a big fan of
Argentina.
I love their footballers.
In 1998 I supported
Which nation did I support? Oh, no, no.
In 1998 I supported France. Sorry.
Yeah, France or Brazil. That's a
different story. Forget about that. So,
I've always supported their football
team because my football team doesn't
even exist in in world football
actually. So,
Yeah, so
I'm a big fan of Argentina, but they are
geopolitically not very important
unfortunately. Brazil is important
because of its enormous size and it's a
big
exporter of various kinds of resources
raw raw materials soybeans or whatnot.
Yeah.
From that perspective it's kind of
somewhat important. And it's also a
member of BRICS which kind of
aligns it softly against the US, but not
very much.
And the US has
singled out Brazil for special
treatment. 50% tariffs the last I heard.
Maybe it's changed now. I'm not sure.
Uh so
look
Are they sovereign or US vassals? Is the
question you're asking at the end.
There are only five sovereign nations in
the world.
That's my answer.
Which are these five sovereign nations?
The US, Russia, China, India and Israel.
No other country is fully sovereign.
And if you are in the Americas, whether
it's North America or South America, you
typically are in some shape or form
to some extent
kind of a US vassal.
Kunal Krish says, "Why do most Russians
hate Stalin now?"
I'm not sure.
Do most Russians hate him?
A lot of them perhaps would hate him.
But I would say that some Russians would
also admire him today.
Um overall look he
is regarded as a very heavy-handed
dictator, a person who caused a lot of
suffering in Russia. Millions of death
deaths happened similar to what Mao did
in in China, but to a in a to a smaller
in a in a smaller way.
So, Stalin did not
cause
the number of deaths of his own people
that's that that Mao did in China, but
he still was a very brutal dictator and
uh
he kind of mismanaged to some extent
some of the governance of his country.
And you had some famines. You had some
forced displacements of the Tatars
into Crimean Crimean Tatars into some
other parts of the of of the country and
so on. So, overall he's regarded as a
very brutal dictator and that's why many
Russians possibly hate him. I'm not sure
if there's a tremendous amount of hate
towards him.
Um
One of the mistakes he did was
assigning Crimea to the Ukrainian SSR
which eventually ended up causing the
crime the the the Ukraine war. I mean
yeah, the Ukraine war and the
re-annexation of Crimea by Russia. So,
multiple factors.
Aman
Patel says, "Isn't
isn't UBI going to be un
going to be inhabitable?
Isn't UBI going to be inhabitable if the
AI and robots take over and a and a huge
chunk of the population
will be jobless, then what will happen
then?"
Universal basic income.
Look, I am of the opinion it's not a
great idea.
For the and then that's probably why
they would
many of the world leaders would wanted
to happen.
Um
Okay, you were trying to say isn't
universal basic income isn't it going to
be inevitable is what you're asking me.
Okay.
If the AI See AI is is is get is
becoming more and more relevant in the
world today. A lot of automation is
happening.
And when you combine AI with robotics,
you're going to have even more
automation
more jobs will
be automated and you will not need
people for that.
So, more people will lose jobs.
And the more this penetrates society as
is inevitable
like you say
uh larger and larger chunks of the
population will kind of become jobless.
What happens then? I think then
then UBI will have to be implemented
universal basic income because people
you know
have to
live, right?
And to live you need a you need
money.
So, I think UBI
is unfortunately something that could
become inevitable.
Yeah.
But that will not be good for the world.
It will not be good for society. It will
lead to all kinds of problems. It will
lead to population collapse.
It will lead to a lot of
dissatisfaction. It will lead to all
kinds of issues.
But it looks like
the way things are going it's clear that
AI
is going to become
something that plays more and more of a
role
in the industry in various industries
all industries.
In 10 years AI may be like essentially
may have taken over significant
percentages of all industries and lots
of people would have possibly lost jobs
especially in developed countries.
Um and also in low-income countries like
India possibly. So, yeah UBI may become
inevitable then. I'm I'm of the opinion
it's a very bad idea, but it may be the
only option left for governments.
So, yeah it's it's quite possible that
it will become
inevitable.
Project Smiling Buddha says, "Indian
e-visa website is ugly and buggy."
IITD foreign admission website same.
IITD okay.
When will we get these basics right?
Frustrating and humiliating. Low
standards. This is the current reality
of India.
Standards.
Things have improved.
For example, there was a time when
getting a passport in the in India used
to take months and months and months. It
was a torturous process. It was a
process of torture that everybody had to
had to undergo unless you had
connections in which case you would get
a passport in a couple of hours.
But most people can't do that, right?
It was torture. Today the passport
process is super streamlined super
painless.
So, things have improved. But still it
depends on who's running what show,
right? The Indian e-visa website is
ugly. So, I don't have to take an Indian
e-visa, so I've not seen the website.
Would you like me to see it? Why not?
Okay.
Um
India
e-visa.
Let's see.
Indian e-visa online gov.in. Looks like
this is the one. The
site cannot be reached. Reload.
Cannot be reached. Reload. Well, well,
well.
Okay.
Looks like they don't want me to see.
Maybe it's available outside India. I
I've no idea. I wasn't able to access
it. My internet connection is working
just fine because I'm able to stream
right now in 4K. So,
Okay, so
I don't know why it's the why it's the
case. It's it's typically a bunch of
bureaucrats that run these things.
And obviously it's for a lot of people
outside of India it will be their first
impression and first interaction with
India the Indian e-visa website. And if
that's a poor experience
half of them will say forget it. I'm not
applying for the visa.
You know, India has the potential to be
a tourism superpower to be the
world's largest tourism destination. But
we aren't anywhere close to it. We are
not sure we are even in the top 10 when
it comes to tourist footfalls
in the world.
It's I mean what on earth is the are the
various ministries doing? Huge L like
they say. Huge huge failure.
Yeah, very very unfortunate, very
frustrating, very humiliating like you
say. Completely agree with you. What can
I what can I say?
It's it's so unfortunate.
Kunal Krish says how to debrainwash
someone about their country. Let's start
with the basics.
First of all, look it will it will only
work if somebody has the willingness to
listen to something that makes them
uncomfortable.
There are things like see brainwashing
happens
progressively over the years. It starts
when you first enter school.
Nursery.
A for apple. It starts from that time.
And then you have junior KG, senior KG,
first, second, third, blah blah blah.
And at each each different level, you
have different forms of brainwashing.
And the teachers don't even realize that
they are brainwashing the kids.
So this is a process that happens over
like 20 years.
And that is something that that
eventually forms the foundation of
everything you believe. So it's a very
uncomfortable thing to even consider
that all the things you believe
and regard as as as as the truth
are far false. So it will So most people
won't even be willing to listen to you
if you want to debrainwash them.
So first of all, the person has to be
willing to go through that experience.
And then you go and and show them the
truth.
And it it once again you have to do it
step by step. Takes time.
Ritwik says please explain current how
the student teacher relation is in India
compared to the west. How bad exactly is
our education system which is still
colonized? Okay. Look, I can't explain
in two minutes. It's not a subject that
can be explained very in in in brief.
But let me Before I answer your
question, let me show you this. Once
again, let's go to my YouTube channel,
okay?
Uh YouTube.
All right, here we are. Let's go to my
channel, YouTube channel.
And I will show you if you want to know
the answer how to
get the answer. Let's go to the oldest
video live streams. And please go to
these episodes over here. Let me Let it
load. Episode 28.
Episode 30, episode 31. In these three
episodes which were streamed like 4
years ago, I have gone into great detail
as to what are the problems that plague
our education system and how the
education system is incredibly harmful
to our civilization. Go through episode
28,
30, 31. I not only talk about what the
problems are, I give clear solutions.
Okay? That's what you should look at if
you are interested in understanding what
the issues are and what the solutions
should be like. I don't believe in
simply complaining boo hoo hoo. If you
complain, you should also give
solutions. I have given solutions.
Now to answer your question, what's the
student teacher relation like?
Tremendous power asymmetry. The
teacher's job
is to impart knowledge, wisdom,
learning, data, and to guide the
students and to ensure that the students
learn skills, they they they acquire
knowledge, and they become more
competent, more proficient,
and more confident and better human
beings. That's supposed to be the job of
a teacher. I believe everybody will
agree with me.
That's what a teacher is supposed to do.
But teachers The average teacher doesn't
do that. The average teacher doesn't
care about that job. The average teacher
wants to play power games.
I think every Indian knows what I'm
talking about.
They want to enforce obedience. Why?
You have to enforce good manners and
civilized behavior, not necessarily
obedience.
In India,
a student has to be you know
You know, if if a teacher likes a
student, what's the best thing they can
say about a student about a student? He
is an obedient student. Very obedient.
That's the best praise a teacher can
give in India.
Not brilliant.
Right? Not original, not creative. No,
obedient.
And what's the best What is the student
the teachers like best?
The student who will be super
deferential, will say, "Teacher, please
can I get up? Teacher, may I sit down?
Teacher, may I go to the toilet?
Teacher, may I come in, teacher?
Teacher, may I breathe, teacher?" That
sort of thing.
They want to create sheep.
Uh and so we have all these problems,
right? That's the issue.
And the the education system, if you
want to understand why it's colonized, I
can't answer in brief. Watch those
episodes. All the answers are there.
S S Phoenix says, "Indians should stop
obsession with institutions and the
government need to convert economic
growth into infrastructure and systems
development. Trump and Putin and Modi et
cetera are are ex and reaction to failed
rules-based technocrat order. Love your
work." Thank you very much. Thank you
very much, sir.
Indians, are they obsessed with
institutions?
Um
Indians, like I said, are are
mentally conditioned to be super
deferential to authority.
You see, anybody who's in a position of
authority, Indians will will will
automatically believe that that person,
whatever they say is right. It is the
word of God.
Indians don't ask questions to They
don't question authority. I'm not saying
revolt. I'm not saying go and do
violence. No, absolutely not. But
question
the accepted wisdom. Question what
people are saying.
Ask yourself, are they doing the right
thing? Can Can things be done better? Is
so-and-so institution serving the
country or serving itself?
Hypothetically.
I'm not naming an institution, by the
way.
Okay?
So is so-and-so institution institution
X,
what is it supposed to actually do? What
role is it actually supposed to play for
the country?
And what is it actually doing?
Indians are are also very polite.
They will not say certain things.
Right?
They will not ask certain questions.
If you ask some great person, "What are
the problems in India today?" They will
say, "Uh
problems like caste is a problem.
Um um and whatever else. Caste is a
problem and political this is a problem,
that is a problem." Sir, is corruption a
problem? Nobody will dare ask.
So there are all these issues and
Indians kind Indians are super
brainwashed. Indians are incapable of
critical thinking. Indians are
mentally lobotomized
through no fault of their own. Indians
are victimized. Indians don't even
realize that they've been victimized.
And that's the issue. The government
needs to convert economic growth into
infrastructure and systems development.
But the money has to be go has to go
somewhere else, right? If you convert
economic growth into infrastructure,
then the money will be used for public
work.
Money is precious, right?
I mean we do infrastructure work every
day.
Every year we rebuild the roads.
We lay a road
We lay roads across the city in in some
hypothetical Indian city. We lay down
the roads. Let's say in
for 6 months of the year we are laying
laying down roads.
From let's say November to May, we are
Then the monsoon comes, rains come.
And by the time the rains are over, we
have dug up the roads again because we
have to we have forgotten to put some
pipes there or whatever.
So then 6 months we will dig up the
roads. Then once again we'll lay down
the roads.
Then once again we'll dig up the roads.
So we are always doing infrastructure
development. Always doing it. Never
ending, sir.
And so on. So this is the problem with
India. Look, in the number one problem
in India
which is keeping India down is the
alleged hypothetical corruption.
Okay?
Um
So uh Trump and Modi and Putin are
reactions to failed rules-based
technocrat order. All right.
Yeah, so that's the that's the issue.
Well, okay. Thank you, sir. Thank you.
Uh Black Boss
says, uh
"Your channel
got recommended to me in May when India
did operation Sindoor. Not everyone here
agrees with our government. Given our
own history, tariffs, sanctions, wars,
empire mentality, will it ever change?
Thank you." I'm assuming assuming that
you are from the US.
Um
I'm sure not everybody agrees with what
the government is doing. I mean that's
how it's supposed to be. You you're
supposed to be a country where you can
disagree with the whatever is is
currently being done. You should have
the right to disagree. You should have
the right to question and you you should
have the right to raise your opinion, to
raise your voice, to voice your
opinions. And I suppose the US does all
of this to to a very great extent, maybe
more more than other parts of the world.
Of course, there are certain things you
can't
do in the US like everywhere else.
Um
Given your own history. Yes,
the US history. We know the
America's history, yeah.
Tariffs, sanctions, wars, empire
mentality. That's kind of what sums up
more recent US history, 20th century
onwards kind of. Will it ever change?
Well, things always change. All empires
rise. Every empire has risen and then
fallen. That's what the world history
tells us. See, history is cyclical in
nature. Cycles, cycles, cycles. Every
single empire See, if you look at India,
we've had so many empires that came and
went within India.
Uh how many can I name very rapidly? The
Mauryan Empire 2500 BC roughly. Then the
Kushan Empire about about 1 100 AD. No,
let's say 0 AD 1 AD. That's the Kushan
Empire. Then you have the Gupta Empire
about 250 300 AD. Then you had a
the Chola Empire 1000 AD. Then you had
the Maratha Empire which is more recent
and so on. Then So all of these empires
came and went. In China you had so many
empires that came and went. You had the
Roman Empire, the Eastern and Western
Roman Empire, the Byzantine Empire, you
had the Ottoman Empire. You can go on
the list is endless. Empires rise and
they fall. Typically an empire lasts
between 250 to 350 years.
Sometimes longer but usually that's the
average length. So the US is an empire.
It is the Roman Empire Redux, the Roman
Empire on steroids. The greatest empire
that ever existed, that's the US today.
Um and
because of that maybe it'll last longer.
Maybe it'll last a thousand years, who
knows.
And as long as an empire
exists, it's going to do everything it
takes
to remain powerful
and to remain the sole hegemon in the
world like the US is today.
It will not tolerate the rise, the
potential rise of other competitors or
adversaries on the horizon and it it
will do whatever it takes to you know
curtail the rise or maybe to end those
potential threats.
And it will do everything it can. Tariff
sanctions, wars, empire mentality, all
of that will be done. Will that ever
change? It will never ever change. Why
will it never change? Human nature.
We are an aggressive warlike species.
We are one of the most aggressive
species that's ever lived on the planet
and um
our closest relatives, the chimpanzees
are just as aggressive if not more as
as aggressive than us, more aggressive
than us.
So that will never change. Even if this
current empire eventually dissolves, new
empires will rise and they will continue
to do the same things.
So as long as humans exist, I suppose
we're going to have this. We are
a violent species, an aggressive
warlike species. I I suppose that will
never change, unfortunately.
Uh
So what what needs to happen then? I I
think you know
it all depends on
to a large extent it depends on culture.
If you if you are from a culture that
that glorifies violence and all that,
then you will have more of that. If you
are from a culture that says, you know,
you should have
temperance, you should you should be
less violent or ideally prioritize
non-violence, then you will have less
warfare and stuff, that sort of thing.
But overall
things won't really change.
Justdeep Suran says, "How did the West
become an advanced society despite being
democratic?" Who says the West is
democratic?
Who says the West is democratic? Can you
please share the last five books you
read? Oh.
And we vote for the 8-hour episode. All
right, we do. Okay. Look,
how did the West become an advanced
society?
What do we mean by advanced society?
First of all, technological advancement.
Secondly, uh powerful military.
Yeah.
Hegemony, military hegemony of the West
and then a good quality of life for the
people.
The West currently gives the gives its
citizens and people who live there the
best quality of life in the world.
Come to India, the West is incredibly
superior to India in terms of quality of
life for the average person.
Basic human dignity, basic all that. How
did the West become so advanced?
To have all of these things,
first of all,
you need money, treasure, gold, wealth,
all of that.
And the West did uh and and how do you
acquire all of that?
Well, one of one way of doing it is by
trading with the world and and providing
values so that you get gold or wealth.
That's one way of doing it. It's a it's
a slow process. Or you can just conquer
the world and destroy everything and
plunder everything.
That's what the West did. They became
incredibly good at the organized
application, organized and scientific
application of violence.
The West perfected that in the past 500
years and they conquered the entire
world. You know, the the Portuguese and
the Spanish
they had the Treaty of Tordesillas
Tordesillas
in which they divided the world into two
halves. You take this, I take that. The
Spanish said, "We will take the Western
Hemisphere." The the Portuguese said,
"We'll take the Eastern Hemisphere." And
they went and colonized whatever they
could.
Um then you have the scramble for Africa
and the whole of Africa was plundered.
And that's by and the British they they
plundered other parts of the world and
they they occupied India for 250 years
and they extracted everything of value
out of India. So these are the means by
which the West became incredibly rich,
incredibly prosperous. And then they
were able to give this quality of life
to their people and obviously they
uh they valued scientific and
technological progress.
And that's how they became an advanced
society and they were never democratic,
they still are not, by the way.
They are not they seem to be democratic
but they're not. Go to Europe and
understand why it's not a democracy.
None of the European nations is
sovereign.
They vote for their presidents or prime
ministers but who rules them? Brussels.
Do you call that a democracy?
Really?
The US I've already explained.
The last five books I read
um I don't know. I've read so many
books.
Uh the one book I was reading today was
Elon Musk's biography by Walter
Isaacson. That's what I was reading
today a couple of a few hours ago.
Um
what else have I been reading? I've been
I don't know. I've
I've got so many books mixed up in my
head. The last one I can think of is
that one.
Right? And you are voting for the 8-hour
episode. All right. Okay, thank you for
for for the vote.
Durgesh says, "Israelis seem to be a
very capable and enter enterprising
population. Why don't they buy a piece
of land in a no conflict zone and live
peacefully?"
Look, they have their own territory.
They have their own country.
The nation of Israel is located
where you had the essentially the the
birthplace of the Jewish people.
Where did the first temple of Solomon
exist?
The first great Jewish temple exist. It
existed in Jerusalem.
It was built about
800 900 AD uh BC.
Right? Jerusalem was a Jewish city from
the very beginning.
So Israel is located exactly where it is
supposed to be located.
It's not Arabic land.
It is Jewish land.
It is the Jewish it's the original
Jewish homeland.
So if it is your original homeland, why
do Indians say that we want POK back?
Because it is also our
ancestral territory, our civilizational
land.
Right? That's why we see and and why do
Indians want Akhand Bharat, expanded
territories of India across the
subcontinent? Because it is our
civilization civilizational territory.
It's always been our territory.
So what's wrong with that? And therefore
what's wrong with Israel wanting
to have a country where their homeland
always existed?
I see nothing wrong with that.
Right?
Ritwik says, "Reply to James. We have
superior climate. Chennai is hot, Ooty
Kodaikanal is cold, all in Tamil Nadu.
Rajasthan is hot desert and also Mount
Abu cold. West only has cold climate.
Europeans are India
Excuse me.
Uh just a second. Let me mm
Uh all right. So
um we have every climate you can
imagine. So I agree with you. Yeah.
If you go to the far north of India, you
have frighteningly cold climate,
essentially Arctic climate, extremely
high altitudes, the Himalayas.
Uh we have desert climate in the Thar
Desert etc. Um
we have archipelagos like the Andaman
and Lakshadweep archipelagos. We have
super hot humid
uh tropical climate down south, Chennai,
Kerala etc. Kerala despite being down
south has a pretty nice cool climate
because of the backwaters and the
forests and so on.
Um
everything you can imagine, all kinds of
terrain.
Everything we have it. Yeah, so
we we we are kind of
perhaps one of the only nation in the
world that has every single climate,
every single kind of
terrain etc. that's available. So
yeah, we're lucky from that perspective.
We certainly are.
EVM says, "Why has ethanol blending
become such a huge controversy when it
allows for reduced reliance on oil
imports and thus decreasing geostrategic
vulnerable vulnerabilities?" I am not
really sure.
I have not studied ethanol blending.
What are the pros and cons, advantage
and advantages and disadvantages? What I
seem to hear
is that maybe it it it
decreases the mileage of vehicles. Maybe
I'm I'm not sure if it's true. This is
what I'm hearing, okay? I'm not saying
it's it's this is the fact.
I'm hearing people complaining.
And what are they complaining about?
Maybe that ethanol blending is
potentially lowering the mileage of
vehicles. That's one complaint I'm
hearing.
Another complaint I'm hearing is that
maybe it it decreases the the lifespan
of engines and
components, perhaps. That's what I'm
hearing. I personally have not studied
this issue
in any sort of detail. I've not even
started studying the issue because
See, so I I look at geopolitics. I'm not
looking at internal matters in India.
So I'm not sure. Maybe maybe it's a true
the real thing, maybe it's a politically
induced controversy, perhaps this,
perhaps that, perhaps a mixture of two
things. I have no idea.
Right?
Certainly it will allow for
you know reduced reliance on oil
imports. Certainly it will allow that.
But
if it has all those other drawbacks,
then people potentially could be unhappy
with that. So, what the truth is, I am
not quite sure. I have not looked into
this matter.
Ideally, we need to find our own oil
within our own territories, and that
should be the end of the whole matter.
Sushant Bharadwaj is a new member. Thank
you very much, sir. Thank you for your
support.
Okay, Sushant Bharadwaj says, "Stay
hydrated, sir. You're precious." Thank
you so much. Let me hydrate a little
more. Thank you very much, sir. Thank
you.
Taking your advice. Thank you very much.
Kunal Krish says,
"Both sides army officials are giving
cryptic cryptic messages
that operation Sindhu 2.0 will begin
soon.
How will the sovereign nation react this
time, US, China, Russia?"
Uh look, it's possible that something
may happen soon. I these cryptic
messages and all this talk talk talk,
words words words, I don't care about.
But it looks like
based on how things are moving,
the Afghanistan situation, the
India-Taliban
um relationship,
and various other factors, it looks like
there could be
a resumption of hostilities between
India and Pakistan.
The US support for Pakistan,
uh and and various other factors, it
looks like it could happen. What will
the other sovereign nations uh what will
their reaction be like, the US,
Russia, and China?
Um it depends on how the if if there is
a war, first of all. It all depends on
how the war goes. The US will support
Pakistan.
But if if the war drags on for like six
weeks,
then everybody will will want to, you
know, interfere in some way in the war.
And uh the longer the war goes, the the
more harmful it is for India,
essentially.
So, if a war happens, we have to end it
in 24 to 72 hours. Achieve your military
and political objectives in that time
frame. Don't let the war drag on for
days and days and days and weeks and
weeks.
Right?
You don't want a Ukraine-like situation,
which will increase the likelihood of
something catastrophic happening on both
sides.
Um and if there's a war, I think the US
will take the the side of the Pakistanis
very openly.
The Chinese will try to stay neutral,
and they will they will request both
sides to
go to the negotiating table, and Russia
will make similar statements. But Russia
will
be on India's side to a larger extent
than being neutral.
The Chinese will remain neutral, and the
US will be openly in support of
Pakistan.
RPPL says, "YouTube and GPT with
competitive market
mark educ-
education says better
PVT."
YouTube and GPT with competitive
market education.
Competitive
education system better
I'm I'm saying I'm assuming you're
saying that YouTube and ChatGPT or AI
will create a better education system.
Is that what you're saying? Better than
private system?
You seem to be saying something
something like that, but it's very
cryptic and very
Okay.
All right, sir.
Okay, GG at India says, "What do you
think
all Biharis
who are in power, bureaucrats looted
India where have the most corrupt system
ever you know know I have No.
I I am not going to go and down this
regional level and start blaming various
regions and various states. We need to
rise above these things, please.
Okay, this is the problem in India that
we keep on pointing fingers at the at
each other.
If the system is allegedly corrupt, it
is not because of one state or another
state. Let's please my rise beyond rise
above this petty mindset, please.
Okay, so yeah.
Shivansh says, "Many federal level
leaders have meetings with the XYZ
authorities in the West.
Is it not dangerous for India, given
that they are already planning to
balkanize India? Can the center not put
push put constraints?"
That's the one of the problems in India.
You see,
the states have too much power. The
states have too much autonomy. The
center is relatively pretty weak
compared to a nation like China. In
China, no official
in a province, no provincial official in
in India we have states, in China we
have provinces, same thing.
In China, no provincial official will
dare to meet
with any foreign official without the
explicit approval of the central
leadership. In India, everything goes.
It's a very big problem in India.
Very big problem in India. And that is
how you play the game of subnational
diplomacy, which is obviously geared
towards potentially balkanizing India in
the future, which is very desirable to
the West.
Can the center not put constraints? I
the center is all constitution Samvidhan
Samvidhan's constitution.
We have to go by the constitution.
Whatever the constitution says, we have
to do. So, then let's balkanize India,
because the constitution will kind of
allow that.
The constitution doesn't recommend or
allow balkanizing India, but it it it
has created a system that's pretty weak.
Right?
Big issue.
Okay, Trupti Joshi says, "Should China
have cooperated more with India, Russia,
Iran? Their current move on allowing
rare earths,
uh but not export to the US, lost lots a
lot of wasted potential."
Um
Should China have cooperated more with
India, Russia, Iran?
Look, China seeks to be
What what has China desired all this
time?
In uh
the late '70s, the Chinese gradually
started opening up their markets to the
US and to the West.
In the '80s, this progressed. By the
1990s, the Chinese became the major
manufacturer of whatever was being uh
I know, whatever
manufacturing the West needed.
In the early 2000s, if you went to the
US,
everything was made in China. So, the
Chinese economy really
um grew exponentially to some extent
because of this, and they became a major
power.
And the Chinese have always had this
great
ambition.
The ambition is what Xi Jinping calls
the great rejuvenation of the Chinese
nation.
The ambition is that they want to
replace and displace the US
as the most powerful nation by about
2050.
That's the objective.
And ever since Mr. Xi Jinping came to
power,
they've been pretty confront-
confrontational with the West and other
countries.
And the Chinese have always regarded
India as a nation that needs to be
balkanized.
They've always regarded
Iran as a nation to be utilized, nation
to be used.
And that's why they have uh
they have this 25-year strategic deal
with Iran,
uh
in which the Iranians will supply China
with
huge quantities of very discounted oil,
and China will help Iran with various
investments, and so on.
And the Chinese have regarded Russia as
an adversary.
Right now, there is a period of time
where they are kind of cooperating
to some extent,
but they they the two nations are
natural adversaries. China is by nature,
the Chinese Communist Party by nature is
this hegemonic entity.
They essentially want to rule the whole
world, and they don't see
that they don't believe that they need
to they need to cooperate with nations.
They believe that they want to they need
to
they need to either use nations
or or or
or super pressurize nations or destroy
nations.
And that's why they have territorial
disputes with almost all their
neighbors, including with Russia.
Well, technically the the dispute with
the with Russia was ended
through an agreement in the early 2000s,
but the Chinese are now reopening those
territorial disputes. They want more
Russian territory.
So, the Chinese have always played this
game. They don't want to cooperate with
anyone. Clearly, wasted potential.
Instead of being the way they are, if
they had sought to cooperate with the
with all their neighbors, it would have
been a much nicer,
you know, part of the world, Eurasia.
But clearly, they they don't see
they don't believe that they they should
behave in that manner. So, clearly, a
lot of wasted potential. Their current
move on allowing rare earths, but not
export to the US, because
see the what they are doing, this this
move about rare earths, or restricting
the exports of rare earths to the US,
it's in retaliation to the US US tariffs
and the US uh
restrictions on semiconductors and chips
to China, exports to China. So, it's
kind of a tit-for-tat move, and the the
Americans have walked into this trap.
The Americans have outsourced all their
rare earths
uh manufacturing and all that to China.
They've been importing all of their rare
earths from China, and they have
neglected developing those industries of
extracting and and purifying rare earths
in the US, and that's why they are
paying the price for that. The Chinese
are simply,
you know, utilizing whatever leverage
they have they have
over the US. So, I don't blame them for
them for that.
Um yeah, so that's that overall is is
the kind of nation China is. So, right
now, India and China will kind of
lower the tensions, but the Chinese will
steadfastly refuse
to demarcate the India-Tibet border. So,
the Chinese are the aggressors with in
in all these territorial disputes.
That's the issue with China. It's a
fundamental problem with the Chinese
Communist Party and its leadership.
Satellite says, "Warm lights or white
lights or Kota lights?" I have no idea
what that is. What is a Kota light?
I don't know what a Kota light is. Warm
lights, white lights, depends on the
situation. If you want to focus, if you
want to study, if you want to do
research, I would say bright white
lights. That keeps you awake, that keeps
you focused. Warm lights, if you want to
relax,
if you want to listen to music, if you
want to spend a couple of hours reading
before you go to bed, warm lights.
Right? And quota lights, I have no idea
what that is. So,
and that's not geopolitics. Why did I
take it?
Rithvik says, we have cold places like
Ladakh, Ooty, Manali, Shimla. We have
great Tawang, Cherrapunji, Shillong. We
have hot places like Jaisalmer,
Jaisalmer, Run of Kutch, islands like
Andaman. Why are we not a tourism
superpower?
That's my question. Why are we not? What
is the Ministry of Tourism doing?
It's not what the Ministry of Tourism
and Culture. Why are we not a cultural
superpower?
What is that Ministry doing?
You know,
it's it's so difficult to reach certain
parts of India. If you are a foreign
tourist,
you are you should
if foreign tourists come to your
country, you should roll out the red
carpet from them for them.
You should give them the best possible
experience.
Tourists aren't treated aren't aren't
treated like that in India.
Some
various officials that treat tourists
like a nuisance.
Tourists also have to pay these
so-called fines.
Or the tourists have to see their
drivers, etc., pay so-called fines to
various
various members of the Indian system,
essentially bribes allegedly.
I mean,
it's it's it's such a low-hanging fruit.
The core issue, once again,
is the alleged corruption.
It's it's it's so it's it's so
unfortunate.
We should be a tourism superpower, but
we're not. It's like we it's like the
government doesn't care at all.
Just like they don't care about the
education system. They don't care about
tourism.
They don't care.
Slogans
is all we do. Slogan, slogan, slogan,
Incredible India. We coined a slogan,
end of story. Ho gaya.
What?
What beyond nothing beyond that, really?
Kavya says, is the judiciary slowing
down the progress of India? Uh no
comments. I discuss geopolitics.
Okay.
Sorry, but I I can't take this question.
Project Smiling Buddha says, Putin went
to Hungary, meet with Zelensky probably,
we'll see. Trump has again started
saying things about stopping this war.
How do you assess the situation?
Trump can't force Putin to do a thing.
If Putin decides that it's worthwhile
meeting with Zelensky,
he may do that.
Uh Trump
Trump has been saying things about
stopping this war since before he became
president second time.
He was claiming he would end the war on
day one of his presidency.
He's super frustrated. This is a huge
failure by him. That's why he's trying
to start other wars and stop them.
How do I assess the situation? The way I
assess the
situation is this.
This war will end on Russia's terms.
This will This war will end on terms
that are acceptable to Russia. It will
not end on terms that are unacceptable
to Russia.
Whatever Putin desires and seeks as the
end state of the war is what will be
achieved by him before he ends the war.
If it is achieved through talking with
Zelensky, he will take that route.
If it is achieved by talking with with
with Trump, he will take that route. If
it is achieved by another 3 years of
grinding warfare, he will take that
route. Whatever happens, this war will
end on Putin's terms, on Russia's terms.
That's how I assess the situation. And
Russia is winning the war, by the way.
The West is not, Ukraine is not.
Please understand that.
I mean,
in 2002, I was saying, Russia will win
the war.
In 2003, I was saying, Russia is
in the ascendancy. Russia is
doing better than Ukraine in the war.
And the comments I used to get,
what's happening now?
I have been saying since day one, the
war will end on Russia's terms.
And I'm still saying that today.
Now, at least nobody is making fun.
Nobody is is is is taunting in the
comments
what I
talking about what I what I was smoking
or whatever. Yeah, really?
People
swallow this propaganda.
The West was saying that Bakhmut Russia
Ukraine is winning. And when Bakhmut was
about to fall, they were saying, why is
why is Russia focusing on Bakhmut, this
irrelevant little town? For the longest
time, they were focusing themselves on
Bakhmut.
Then they were saying, Putin is dying of
cancer. He's got 3 months to live. They
were saying in 2022. What happened?
Please stop swallowing propaganda.
Please think critically. That's what I
would say. So, the way I see it, the war
will end on Russia's terms, whatever is
what the Russians assess to be
uh what they want what they
the outcome that they they desire out of
this war.
Animesh says, thank you for helping us
evolve and become a better version of
ourselves. Thank you so much. I I you're
very welcome, and yeah, that that's all
I seek to do.
That's all I seek to do, nothing else.
Thank you.
Anand says, why can't the government ban
pan or gutkha in India?
Uh they are building infrastructure, but
some people are making it look bad by
spitting pan, gutkha. Uh as per you,
what is going wrong here? I think that
Look, similarly, they can also ban
alcohol, they can also ban tobacco,
cigarettes, and whatnot. But they don't.
I think
the thing is that, you know,
in any society, you have to allow people
to to do some vices, some things that
are not good.
And you can tax them. And you can tax
them tax those things heavily. I know
pan, gutkha it it
and people end up spitting all over the
place, and that's disgusting.
Uh
but I think a lot of people
consume that that that horrible thing.
And if you ban it, then you will lose
votes, I suppose.
So, maybe that's the reason why.
Uh I don't know what the reason is. I I
You know,
in every country, they allow all these
all these products. But in in India, you
have this this terrible thing of pan and
gutkha.
So, the only reason I can imagine is
that if you if you ban this, then lots
of people will will vote vote against
you.
That's what I imagine. I think it looks
like a lot of people are consumers of
this disgusting thing.
My perspective disgusting, maybe for
some people it's it's great.
It's your choice. So, that's
possibly the reason why the government
is not doing it, and they're
potentially earning big revenues from
that by taxing that. I think the taxes
on these uh sin products are pretty
high, right?
Uh whether it is alcohol or or tobacco
or pan, gutkha, whatever, the taxes are
pretty steep. So, yeah, win-win but
potentially for the government.
All right, I think we are done with the
questions. I have think we have covered
all the super chats. So, I can now end
this
stream here.
Uh
okay.
So, what is this gutkha and cigarette
should be banned? I suppose if it's bad
for
society, if it's bad for people's
health.
I'm sure lots of people want to quit
these products, but they can't because
they're addicted. So, if you if you ban
it, I think some at least some will be
happy.
Um
Celebrities promote them, says Lavanya.
That's true. Yeah, a lot of money in
this, isn't it? Yeah.
Um
Tobacco industry pays heavy taxes,
that's why. Yeah, that's one reason,
right? Big steep taxes.
Steep taxes.
Ayush says, okay, let's make this the
last question for today. Ayush says, on
the surface, it it seems like the
Taliban is a vassal of the US. What's
the case? Can't India take the base
which US wants?
As Taliban is more trustful to us, at
least on the surface. My my thoughts.
Okay.
Look, there the Taliban was handed power
by the US. The Taliban
came back to power in in Afghanistan
because the Americans gave them
Afghanistan back.
The US wanted to leave Afghanistan. So,
they made a secret deal with the
Taliban, the Doha Accord, which has some
secret clauses.
And it has been alleged very strongly by
various very reputable people that the
US has been paying the Taliban a weekly
stipend between 30 to 100 million
dollars in cash.
Okay?
So, that would be in exchange for
certain services that the Taliban would
render for the US, like keeping China
out of Afghanistan, and so on.
So, that was the accord. That was Those
were the terms of the accord, I imagine.
Okay? Secret terms. Now, the Americans
want things that were not agreed upon.
They want Bagram. In the Doha Accord, I
can promise you there was no deal about
Bagram that the Taliban has to give
Bagram to America.
Now, the Americans are demanding things
like that. So, the Taliban will say, no,
absolutely not.
We will
honor the accord that we had. We will
agree We have agreed to certain terms.
We are taking your money, so we'll make
sure that we will not allow China to
come into Afghanistan and and you know,
use our territory for whatever they want
to do. All those things we will do as
per the agreement. But you can't make
extra demands.
So, the Taliban isn't a vassal of the
US. They have an agreement with the US,
which a sovereign nation can have.
Okay? Why can't India take the base?
Well, that's
Um I think Taliban doesn't want anybody
any foreign military in the country. And
I think we should respect that. Okay?
That's what I That's my That's how I see
it.
Uh it looks like there are a couple more
super chats. Um
Okay, Amisha is a new member. Thank you
so much, ma'am. Thank you very much.
Um
Ankita says, "If we wish to see a Viksit
Bharat,
a drastic change in the system is sort
of compulsory. There's no other choice."
Yeah, you're right.
Uh which domain would be a good starting
point according to you? Judiciary,
bureaucracy, education, or others?
I would say but
the starting point has to be to end
corruption wherever it exists.
It has to start with a war on
corruption. Here's a Here's
maybe a completely
impractical solution.
Let's Let's do a thought experiment. How
experiment?
I'm sure everybody understands to what
extent corruption allegedly exists in
the country.
How much of public money is allegedly
hypothetically being diverted through
corruption?
Tremendous amounts, right?
So, how about the government
unilaterally
increases the salaries of all government
employees 10 times?
If you are receiving X, from next month
you will receive 10 X. But now, if you
get caught doing corruption, the penalty
is extremely steep.
That sort of thing. So, maybe something
like that
could be done.
I would say that the first thing need
that needs to happen urgently,
desperately needed is
a war on corruption.
Without So, that's what I I would say.
Whichever institution, whichever domain
it exists in, I'm sure there are some
domains with the where there is no
corruption. I'm sure.
But wherever it exists allegedly,
this needs to happen. Without that,
nothing is going to change in India.
I would say that is the starting point.
That is That is the right starting
point. Okay?
Thank you, Ankita ji. Always good to
have your questions.
Shivansh says, um
maybe not geopolitical, but since the
region creates headlines over
creates headlines, why have we failed to
inhabit Pandits or anyone else for that
matter back in Kashmir? The government
boasts
uh revoking Article 370 as a success.
Beats me.
What is the point of revoking that
article
if there is no change on the ground?
You change something on paper.
Why haven't the native inhabitants of
Kashmir be
Why haven't they been resettled in their
homeland?
I don't know.
I have no idea.
I have no idea. I don't have an answer.
And it's very disappointing.
Okay, Kiran says, "Thank you for your
effort, brother. Happy Diwali to you and
your audience." Thank you, Kiran ji.
Thank you so much. Happy Diwali to you
as well and to your family and loved
ones and to the audience as well. Thank
you very much.
Prashant says, "Please Please explain
the Peru situation, corruption plus T."
I'm not sure what's the situation. I
haven't been paying attention to Peru.
What happened there?
If you ask me about Peru, I will talk
about the Inca Empire.
That's 500 years ago.
And maybe that's the root cause of all
the situation there, but I am not aware
of what's happening right now. Let's
quickly Google it.
Peru situation. Uh By the way, please
stop taking super chats. I want to end
the live stream now. It's like 2 and 1/2
hours.
Uh Peru, what's happening? Peru news.
What's going on? Gen Z protest. Oh god.
Oh god, no. Gen Z protests. So, the new
So, the new version of the color
revolution template is the Gen Z
protests. Now, put everything in the
name of Gen Z.
Looks like the the Americans are trying
a new regime change operation there for
whatever reason. I'll I'll check it out,
but right now I don't have the details.
All right. Ankita says, "Happy Diwali,
sir." Thank you, ma'am. Happy Diwali to
you as well and to your loved ones.
Thank you, ma'am.
And the last question is by Satellite
Arrogant KBC Kid. Any comments? I have
no idea. Which KBC kid?
Arrogant kid.
I I'm not aware of this. Sorry.
I'm sure it's not geopolitical, so I
won't be able to say.
Okay, people. This is the end of today's
session. Thank you, everybody for all
your questions, for your viewership. I
always appreciate that.
I'm very privileged to have you as my
viewers. So, thank you so much.
And um
yeah, I look forward to you to seeing
you in next week's live streams. Thank
you, everybody. Happy Diwali to
everybody. Good day. Shub Ratri.
Good night wherever you are in the
world.
Thank you so much and I'll see you in
the next one. Thank you.
Good night. Bye-bye. Keep raising your
standards as always. Bye-bye.